<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the government of churches; a discourse pointing at the primitive form.</title>
            <author>Thorndike, Herbert, 1598-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1102_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863603</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863603</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115813</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 163:E1102[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the government of churches; a discourse pointing at the primitive form.</title>
                  <author>Thorndike, Herbert, 1598-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 208 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel, printer to the Universitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Herbert Thorndike.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "by Herbert Thorndirk".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115813:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the</hi> GOVERNMENT OF CHURCHES; <hi>A diſcourſe</hi> Pointing at the Primitive Form.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Roger Daniel,</hi> Printer to the Univerſitie of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115813:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115813:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Gracious JAMES, <hi>Duke of</hi> Lennox, <hi>Earl of</hi> March, <hi>&amp;c. L. Warden of the Cinque Ports, Knight of the moſt Noble Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Garter, and one of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties most Honourable Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, his very good</hi> LORD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe your Grace. The advantage this ſlight worthleſſe piece aimeth at, in this addreſſe, is of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, but of a civil and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate nature. It is no marvel if it deſire to go forth under ſo
<pb facs="tcp:115813:3"/> great a Name, that is not like to appear conſiderable to the world otherwiſe. But the Countenance it demandeth, is according as the cauſe may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve: more it muſt not expect from your Juſtice, leſſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect from your Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If it fail of the Truth, it is a Child rebellious to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers intentions, and according to the Law of Moſes, here he bringeth him forth to receive his doom. If it have any thing conſiderable in a Cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the world is ſo well informed
<pb facs="tcp:115813:3"/> long ſince, my ſuit is, that from your Graces hands it may be derived to the publick. The Lord of Heaven and Earth bleſſe your Grace with happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this life, and of that which is to come. So prayes</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt humble Chaplain, <hi>HERBERT THORNDIKE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115813:4"/>
            <head>To the Lovers of Peace and Truth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat ſtyle muſt ſerve me for a Preface to this ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. The love of Peace and Truth, my hope is, hath made ſome Impreſsion in the reaſons where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it proceedeth: And it were a wrong to the world to think that thoſe marks can be offenſive. My purpoſe was, to contribute towards the true meaning of the Scripture in theſe matters: If I have failed of it, the attempt will deſerve your excuſe. But my heart telleth me not that I have ſet any Text on the
<pb facs="tcp:115813:4"/> rack to make it confeſſe more then it means. Eccleſiaſticall writers, I have for the moſt part ſtripped of the authoritie which their years &amp; merits in the Church have wonne, and produced them as witneſſes at the Bar of common ſenſe, to make evidence from the Hiſtoricall truth of their ſayings. The meaning of them is for the moſt part either tranſlated by their words, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the current of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Sometimes it is left to every mans apprehenſion to value: for when all is done, men muſt and will be judges for themſelves.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:115813:5"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. <hi>line</hi> 18. <hi>ac providè</hi> reade <hi>ac proinde. p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 5. expreſſed <hi>r.</hi> expreſſeth. <hi>p.</hi> 58. <hi>l.</hi> 3. becauſe <hi>r.</hi> became. <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 19. theſe <hi>r.</hi> thoſe. <hi>l.</hi> 21. theſe <hi>r.</hi> thoſe. <hi>p.</hi> 83. <hi>l.</hi> 20. Synagogues <hi>r.</hi> Synagogue. <hi>p.</hi> 85. <hi>l.</hi> 14. after elſe, <hi>adde.</hi> And the chief cauſes in Religion brought to no Court but this. <hi>p.</hi> 87. <hi>l.</hi> 19. after writeth, <hi>adde In Hilcoth Sanedrin. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 102. <hi>l.</hi> 9. thoſe <hi>r.</hi> theſe. <hi>p.</hi> 114. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>Baptiſt. r. Baptiſmo. p.</hi> 119. <hi>l.</hi> 5. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſing <hi>r.</hi> diſpenſing. <hi>p.</hi> 129. <hi>l.</hi> 1. Tertullian: <hi>r.</hi> Tertullian) <hi>p.</hi> 131. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>Toreh r. Joreh. p.</hi> 140. <hi>l.</hi> 22. ſome <hi>r.</hi> ſound. <hi>p.</hi> 147. <hi>l.</hi> 24. alwayes <hi>r.</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes. <hi>p.</hi> 151. <hi>l.</hi> 5. after heart <hi>adde</hi> being. <hi>p.</hi> 183. <hi>l.</hi> 11. and <hi>r.</hi> of.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115813:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles eye-witneſſes of our Lord, and eare-witneſſes of his doctrine. S. Paul an Apoſtle. Many perſonall qualities in them. They were Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of Churches.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that deſireth to eſpie light at a narrow hole, muſt lay his eye near, if he mean to diſcover at large: So muſt he be curious in conſidering the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that meaneth to diſcern thoſe things that are not declared there at large, but are collected by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or conſequence: eſpecially in matters which we view at this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, which repreſenteth to us things done then through a miſt of ſucceeding cuſtome. Thoſe that ſeek for mines, have their <hi>virgula divina,</hi> a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115813:6"/> rod which they hold even-balanced over the place where they hope for a vein, which if it hit right, the rod of it ſelf bendeth towards the earth: Our Lord in the Goſpel command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to ſearch the Scriptures as men would ſeek for mines or treaſure; let us keep an even balance of judgement, not bowing, but as the vein of truth ſwayeth it: for if we put the grains of affection and prejudice into the gold-ſcales which we weigh nice truths with, no marvel if the lighter go down. Now becauſe the queſtion concerneth the Apoſtles time, and the next to it, and the purpoſe is to repreſent the form pointed at in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, by comparing it with ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of hiſtoricall truth and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive practice as ſhall ſeem beſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, let us in the firſt place conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the nature of their charge, that it may appear how farre the Church reteineth a ſucceſſion of it. For true
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115813:6"/> it is, divers perſonall qualities are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in an Apoſtle, becauſe they were to preach the Goſpel to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. They muſt be men to witneſſe thoſe things they had ſeen our Lord do, thoſe words they had heard him ſpeak, upon their own knowledge; and therefore men that had converſed with him from the beginning of his doctrine. It is that S. Peter required at the choice of Matthias, Acts i. 21. <hi>Of theſe men that have companied with us all the while that the Lord Jeſus went in and out among us, muſt one be ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a witneſſe of his reſurrection with us.</hi> It is that the ſame Apoſtle chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth, 1. Pet. v. 1. <hi>The elders which are among you I exhort, who am alſo an elder, and a witneſſe of the ſufferings of Chriſt.</hi> He condeſcendeth to the rank of Presbyters, when he ſaith, <hi>who am alſo an Elder;</hi> but he voucheth the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of an Apoſtle, when he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>and a witneſſe of the ſufferings of</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115813:7"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And his fellow-Apoſtle of the Gentiles to the ſame purpoſe, 1. Corinth. ix. 1. <hi>Am I not an Apoſtle? am I not free? have I not ſeen Jeſus Chriſt our Lord?</hi> as if to be an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle required one that had ſeen the Lord, which was ſupplyed to him by his raptures and viſions, as the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his doctrine was ſupplyed unto him by that revelation by which he avoucheth to have received his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, in the beginning of his Epiſtle to the Galatians. This is that God had provided for ſatisfaction of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe; men that could witneſſe upon the credit of their eyes and eares what they publiſhed. But it required greater matters to convince the world of thoſe things which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon could not evidence: The gifts of the holy Ghoſt, for knowledge, for language, for miracles, for all the like were requiſite in a marvellous nature for thoſe that undertook to preach
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115813:7"/> the Goſpel to all nations. This was the Apoſtles charge; and the power this charge importeth, the indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments it requireth, are perſonall, wherein no man pretendeth to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Apoſtles: But the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this charge reaſon telleth us muſt needs proceed, and experience of that which is written telleth us it did proceed, according to the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of their ſeverall opportunities, concerted by conſent among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: For ſo we find the chief A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Gal. ii. 9. dividing their care between the Jews and the Gentiles. If it appear then that the Apoſtles, for their time, took upon them the overſight of Churches of their own planting, if it appear that an Apoſtle fixed his abode and care both upon ſome Church in ſeverall, though all the world were their Dioceſe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, well may we proceed upon theſe terms, to make the Apoſtles
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115813:8"/> Biſhops of ſuch and ſuch Churches, and Biſhops ſucceſſours of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; though neither for the extent of their charge, nor for their abilities to perform it, yet becauſe they are truſted with that overſight of one Church, which the Apoſtles for their time afforded to all within their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church of Jeruſalem under the charge of James and his Presbyters. This was James ſonne of Alpheus. How he was brother of our Lord. Cleophas and Alpheus both one.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THis is that we muſt ſtand upon in the firſt place, to averre the firſt pattern of the form, after which it ſhall appear that Churches were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned from the beginning by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their Presbyters. It is to be ſeen in the firſt Church, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115813:8"/> Church of Jeruſalem, Mother of all Churches, which we ſhall find under the charge of James of Jeruſalem one of the Apoſtles, and his Presbyters, no doubt by conſent and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apoſtles, providing for the Church there before their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from it. Wherein we ſhall not need to ſet up our reſt upon the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of Ignatius or Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus (though either of them of age ſufficient to witneſſe as great a matter as this) having ſo many pregnant paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Scripture to averre it. The Apoſtle, relating his going up to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem to ſee Peter, Gal. i. 18. proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth it thus in the next words, <hi>But other of the Apostles ſaw I none, but James the brother of the Lord.</hi> How cometh he to meet James at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem when he went to ſee Peter there, more then the reſt of the Apoſtles, but becauſe he abode there at his charge? And again, Galat. ii. 9. <hi>And</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115813:9"/> 
               <hi>when James, Peter and John, who ſeemed to be pillars, ſaw the grace of God that was given to me,</hi> &amp;c. we ſhall not need to think James is put in the firſt place for nothing, when we have ſo fit a reaſon to give for it, becauſe they were then all at the place of his charge: for ſo you ſhall find it again in that moſt conſiderable action, of the Councel at Jeruſalem, Acts xv. 7, 13. The decree of the Councel as it is reſolved upon S. Peters reaſons, ſo is it framed and drawn up in S. James his terms, verſ. 7, 13. the one as firſt of the Apoſtles, the other as having the charge of the Church there: which ſtill further appeareth by that which is read Gal. ii. 12. that <hi>before ſome came from</hi> S. <hi>James,</hi> S. <hi>Peter ate with the Gentiles; but when they came, he withdrew and ſeparated himſelf, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe of the circumciſion.</hi> We ſee S. Peter taketh adviſe of S. James; as likewiſe afterwards S. Paul at his laſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115813:9"/> coming to Jeruſalem, Acts xxi. 19. went in to James where all the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were preſent, to adviſe with him that had the care of that Church, about the great buſineſſe in hand, how to behave himſelf towards thoſe of the circumciſion that believed. Now of the Colledge of Presbyters at Jeruſalem, and of their concurrence and aſſiſtance with this James in the government of the Church there, we have three unreprovable arguments in the Acts of the Apoſtles. The firſt, in diſpoſing the maintenance of the poore, whereof we reade Acts xi. 30. that the benevolence of the Church of Antiochia, was ſent to the Elders at Jeruſalem by the hands of Saul and Barnabas to be diſpoſed of by them, but miniſtred and laid out by the Deacons, as ſhall be ſhewed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. The ſecond is found in the paſſage of the Councel at Jeruſalem, wherein their concurrence appeareth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115813:10"/> in that which is reſolved, Acts xv. 2. that <hi>Paul and Barnabas ſhould go up to Jeruſalem to the Apoſtles and Elders, about that queſtion.</hi> And verſe 4. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to Jeruſalem, they are received of the Apostles and Elders.</hi> Again, verſe 6. <hi>The Apostles and Elders came together to conſider of this matter.</hi> And verſe 22. <hi>It pleaſed the Apostles and Elders with the whole Church, to ſend choſen men of their own company to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch with Paul and Barnabas.</hi> And the letter in the next verſe runneth in the name of the Apoſtles and Elders. All to argue the concurrence and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Presbyters with the Apoſtles, which were then preſent there, beſides James which had the particular charge. The third is, that which hath been remembred, at S. Pauls laſt going to Jeruſalem, where we find the Elders, aſſembled with James, as his aſſiſtants in adviſing with S. Paul about the matter on foot: for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115813:10"/> it is plain, that the advice whereupon he proceedeth in a matter of that weight is given him by James, and the Presbyters both, as we reade there, verſe 20. <hi>And they ſaid unto him,</hi> that is, James and the Elders. This James of Jeruſalem I make no ſcruple to reckon among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, becauſe S. Paul hath done it afore me: For it is plain that he ſpeaketh of no other but the Twelve ſo called by our Lord from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, Luke vi. 13. Becauſe of them the queſtion might have been made, whether he had received his doctrine from them or not, which he there denieth: And therefore it is plain this James can be no other then James ſonne of Alpheus reckoned in the Goſpels among the Twelve, James the ſonne of Zebedee, brother of John being put to death by Herod before, Acts xii. 2. On the other ſide, when S. Paul calleth him <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115813:11"/> 
               <hi>of our Lord,</hi> without doubt he meaneth no other but him that is called in the Goſpels, <hi>James the leſſe,</hi> brother of Joſes and ſonne of Mary, Matth. xxvii. 56. Mark xv. 43. the ſame Mary no doubt that is called, John xix. 25. <hi>Mary of Cleophas,</hi> ſiſter to the bleſſed Virgin. Firſt, becauſe theſe Goſpels ſpeak of the ſame wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that ſtood by our Saviours croſſe; and again, becauſe the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of our Lord are reckoned, Mark vi. 13. James, and Joſes, and Judas, and Simon. So that all the difference that hath been about the ſeverall Jameses and Maries remembred in the Goſpel, is extinguiſhed by making Alpheus and Cleophas both one in the language then in uſe, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers wayes written in the Greek. A thing nothing ſtrained: For though Cleophas be otherwiſe written in the Syriack, becauſe it is tranſlated out of the Greek, yet the Syriack
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115813:11"/> name CHALPAI may be expreſſed either by <hi>Alpheus</hi> or <hi>Cleophas,</hi> which is alſo written <hi>Clopas</hi> in ſome copies, John xix. 25. and in Hegeſippus quoted by Euſebius, <hi>Eccleſ. hist. iii.</hi> 23. This I perceive ſince the writing hereof, to be the opinion of Lud. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellus, who hath alledged S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome againſt Helvidius to ſtrengthen it, where he maketh Mary of Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas, ſiſter of the bleſſed Virgin, the wife of Alpheus and mother of James the leſſe: Wherewith agreeth Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus in Euſebius, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hiſt. ii.</hi> 1. where he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth but two Jameses, the ſon of Zebedee, and this James of Jeruſalem mentioned by the Apoſtle. And herewith agreeth S. Chryſoſtome, upon that text of the Apoſtle, where he obſerveth that for S. James his honour S. Paul calleth him <hi>brother of our Lord,</hi> whereas he might as well have called him <hi>ſonne of Cleophas,</hi> as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115813:12"/> the Evangeliſt had done. Here it is plain that James the brother of our Lord and ſonne of Cleophas, is the Apoſtle ſonne of Alpheus, according to S. Chryſoſtome. As for that which followeth, that nevertheleſſe he was not of kin to our Lord accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh, but according to the opinion of the world, it ſeemeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon Hegeſippus in Euſebius, iii. 11, 26. where he maketh Cleophas brother to Joſeph, ſuppoſed father of our Lord. Which is poſſible to be true, that Joſeph and Cleophas bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhould take to wife the two Maries, ſiſters or couſins: But other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there is ſo much appearance in the Goſpel, that Mary mother of James and Joſes, is Mary of Cleophas ſiſter to the bleſſed Virgin, that it muſt needs be an inconvenience to deny this James to be kin to our Lord by her ſide. As for other rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conjectures of Church-writers,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115813:12"/> the varietie whereof is end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and unreconcilable, it is not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to draw them into conſequence to the prejudice of a conjecture which maketh ſo clear an agreement of this whole difference. It was my deſire to ſhew the true meaning of the Apoſtles words; but it is not my purpoſe to build upon uncertainties. Whoſoever this James of Jeruſalem was, we find the Church of Jeruſalem under his charge, almoſt aſſoon as there was a Church there, at leaſt if we believe Ignatius, <hi>Epiſt. ad Trall.</hi> where he ſaith, S. Stephen was Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con to this James of Jeruſalem, which muſt be betimes after our Lords death. And therefore thus we ſee whom the Biſhops of Jeruſalem ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115813:13"/>
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Apoſtles planted mother-churches in mother-cities. The Government of them eſtated upon Preſbyteries. Saint Paul at the beginning made no Biſhops over thoſe Preſbyteries. The reaſon. Himſelf had the overſight of the Churches of his planting for the time. The like in the Churches of S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters charge.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>LEt us now go abroad with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſee how they follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this pattern in the Churches which they converted to the faith. Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>l. De praeſcript. c.</hi> 20. ſpeaketh thus of them, <hi>ac providè Eccleſias apud una<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quamque civitatem condiderunt.</hi> This ſlight circumſtance which he but pointeth at, that the Apoſtles found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches in Cities, is very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in our buſineſſe. For it is plain they could not beſtow their pains on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115813:13"/> all places: reaſon required they ſhould labour moſt to plant the faith in the moſt populous. And common ſenſe and the leaſt knowledge of times will ſerve to ſhew, that from thence it was propagated through the Countreys that lay to thoſe Cities, which therefore in time became and were called the Territories, Pariſhes, or Dioceſes of ſuch or ſuch Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Now the form of government eſtated by S. Paul over theſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es is pointed out to us Acts xiv. 23. where we reade in the end of their firſt journey that Paul and Barnabas, <hi>having ordained them Presbyters in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Church,</hi> returned to Antiochia. But unto Titus the Apoſtle writeth thus, Tit. i. 5. <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in Crete, that thou mighteſt ſet in order the things that are wanting, and conſtitute Elders in every city, as I had appointed thee. Elders in every Church</hi> in the one place, and <hi>Elders in every city</hi> in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115813:14"/> other; both to the ſame effect: not meaning one in a place, but Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, that is Colledges, bodies, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Presbyters, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon advice to order the Churches planted in theſe Cities. Such a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Presbyters it was that we ſpoke of in the laſt chapter, inſtituted by the Apoſtles in the Church of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, the pattern whereof S. Paul followeth in the Churches which he converted out of the Gentiles. And thus in the Church of Epheſus, you ſhall ſee S. Paul, Acts xx. 17. ſending for the bench of Elders there to Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Thus in the Church of Philippi, you ſhall find that the Apoſtle direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Epiſtle to the Biſhops and Deacons there, which muſt be to the Colledge of Presbyters, next above the order of Deacons. Thus when the Apoſtle writeth to the Theſſalonians, 1. Theſſ. v. 12. <hi>And we beſeech you, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to know them which labour among</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115813:14"/> 
               <hi>you, and are over you in the Lord,</hi> the multitude whereof he ſpeaketh, is to be underſtood of the like company of Presbyters. Thus in Ignatius his epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, you ſhall find him up and down reckoning next after the Biſhops the Presbyteries of all the Churches to which he writeth. The like in S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians epiſtles, for the Presbyteries of Rome and Carthage. To ſpare more words, in all Church-writers you ſhall find continuall remembrance of theſe Presbyteries, whenſoever there is ſpeech of Mother-churches in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cities: And therefore thoſe we are to underſtand, when we reade that Paul and Barnabas ordained Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>in every Church,</hi> and Titus <hi>in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry City:</hi> And ſuch Bodies or Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Presbyters they were to whom the Apoſtle committed the Churches which he had planted. But this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted, the queſtion will be in the next place, Where are the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115813:15"/> the chief and heads of theſe Presbyteries? For had the Apoſtle from the beginning of his planting theſe Churches placed that rank over theſe Presbyters, it is like we ſhould have found ſome remembrance of it. Now theſe Presbyters are ſtyled by the name of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ever ſince S. Hierome; and which is more, to averre the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for this purpoſe, neither in the relation of his planting and ordering the Churches, nor in the ſtyle of his Epiſtles, nor in his inſtructions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning miniſters of theſe Churches, is there any remembrance or reſpect to be found but of Presbyters and Deacons, which in ſo much emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of place, ſo much difference of Biſhops office, if any then had been, could ſcarce have come to paſſe: and maketh me conclude, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ordained none ſuch from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning over the Presbyteries. No
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115813:15"/> Biſhop the Apoſtle had yet ſettled at Epheſus, when he uſed theſe words to the Presbyters there, Acts xx. 17. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves and to the whole flock over whom the holy Ghoſt hath made you</hi> EPISCOPOS, <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers.</hi> For as he giveth the name to the Presbyters, ſo he addreſſeth his inſtructions to none beſides. None at Philippi, when he directed his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Biſhops and Deacons</hi> there, neither the cuſtome of the Church bearing more then one Biſhop in one Church at once, nor being a thing reaſonable to think if any ſuch had been, that the Apoſtle would not have found a room for him in the ſtyle of his Epiſtle. None in the Churches within the charge of Timothy and Titus (ſet aſide their own perſons, whereof we ſhall give account after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) in whoſe inſtructions the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is large in qualifying Biſhops and Deacons, (ſuch Biſhops as we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115813:16"/> reade of Tit. i. 7. where, having ſaid that <hi>he left him in Crete to make Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters in every city,</hi> the Apoſtle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>For a Biſhop muſt be blameleſſe)</hi> but of any other rank not a ſyllable. None in the Church of Corinth. The Commentaries under S. Ambroſe his name yield this reaſon of the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Apoſtle taxeth there, 1 Cor. xi. 21. Becauſe there was no Biſhop there. The words are not of ordinary mark: <hi>Hos notat qui ſic in Eccleſiam conveniebant, ut munera ſua offerentes, advenientibus Presbyteris, quia adhuc Rectores Eccleſiis non omnibus locis fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant conſtituti, totum ſibi qui obtulerat vindicaret ſchiſmatis causâ.</hi> So where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that whereof the Euchariſt was conſecrated ſhould be ſpent by the aſſembly in the common feaſt of Love, ſome made good chear, others that had not offered went away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their ſhare. Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, ver. 22. <hi>Have ye not houſes to</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115813:16"/> 
               <hi>eat and drink in? but deſpiſe ye the Church of God?</hi> coming thither for diſſenſions ſake and belly-chear, not for the Sacrament and for peace? <hi>and ſhame them that have not,</hi> ſending them away without enterteinment? therefore verſe 33. he exhorteth to <hi>ſtay for one another</hi> at their meetings. Thus farre out of thoſe Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Which reaſon, as it giveth a clear meaning to the whole paſſage of the Apoſtle; ſo it groweth ſtill more probable, becauſe we ſhall find after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that it continueth ſtill in force at the time of writing Clemens his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle publiſhed not long ſince. And men of learning have argued, that this reaſon might better be yielded for their diſſenſions, <hi>ſaying, I am of Paul, I am of Apollos, I am of Cephas,</hi> which the Apoſtle reproveth in the beginning of the Epiſtle, to wit, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was then no Biſhop there, and in the Apoſtles abſence. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115813:17"/> if we reckonnot amiſſe, what reaſon have we to think, that this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſhould ordain in the Churches of his planting a higher rank of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to govern the Churches, above and with the Presbyters? Do we not ſee that he chargeth himſelf with the overſight of theſe Churches wherein he had planted the Colledges of Presbyters aforeſaid, 2. Corinth. xi. 28. <hi>Beſides thoſe things which are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that which cometh upon me dayly, the care of all the Churches?</hi> To what purpoſe elſe is the journey he taketh, Acts xv. 36. to viſit the Churches wherein he had ordained Presbyters afore? <hi>Let us return,</hi> ſaith he to Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas, <hi>and viſit our brethren in all ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties where we preached the word of the Lord, and ſee how they do.</hi> We ſee he taketh care to exerciſe diſcipline up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inceſtuous perſon at Corinth, which it ſeemeth the Rulers of the Church there had neglected to do,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115813:17"/> 1. Cor. v. 4. pronouncing ſentence of excommunication, and requiring the Church to ſee it ratified &amp; executed. And for a thing remarkable, obſerve in what terms he proceedeth, 1. Cor. v. 4. <hi>When ye are gathered together, and my ſpirit,</hi> ſaith he, his <hi>Spirit,</hi> which ruled there in chief for the time. So that it is not for nothing that Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian <hi>lib. De praeſcript. cap.</hi> 36. reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Corinth, Philippi, Theſſalonica, Epheſus, and the reſt of the ſame rank, all Apoſtolicall Churches, from this one Apoſtle, becauſe he planted and ruled them all for his time: <hi>Apud quas,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ipſae adhuc cathedrae Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuis locis praeſident,</hi> which is in good Engliſh neither more nor leſſe then here is affirmed; The Apoſtles chair reſted in them all till Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans time, therefore the Apoſtle for his time ſate in it. And to my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, all his Epiſtles are nothing elſe but ſo many acts of this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115813:18"/> ſpirituall in chief, which the Apoſtle reſerved himſelf in the Churches of his own planting. The like to be ſaid of S. Peters Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and hath been obſerved in part by Euſebius, <hi>Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. iii. cap.</hi> 5. That the title of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Epiſtle addreſſed to <hi>the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers diſperſed through Pontus, Aſia, Galatia, Cappadocia, and Bithynia,</hi> that is, to the Jews ſojourning in thoſe provinces, argueth it to be a work of his care, in preaching the Goſpel to the charge he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, according to the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alledged before, Galat. ii. 9. And therefore, as hath been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to argued of the other Apoſtle, ſo when we ſee S. Peter, 1. Pet. v. 1. direct his exhortation to <hi>feed the flock</hi> to none but Presbyters, we have cauſe to conceive that thoſe Churches to whom he writeth, and whom we ſhall heare Epiphanius
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115813:18"/> ſay anon that he went ſometimes from Rome to viſit, had as yet no Biſhops over their Presbyters. The ſame that S. Hierome hath argued long ſince out of Hebr. xiii. 17. where the Apoſtle writeth in the plurall number, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115813:19"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>As the Apoſtles withdrew, ſo Biſhops came over the Presbyteries in their ſtead. Timothy and Titus had not their charge till S. Paul left thoſe parts. His journey from Epheſus through Macedonia into Greece. By the way he left Titus in Crete. Why he wintered at Nicopolis. At ſpring he returned by land into Macedonia. There and then Timothy undertaketh the Church of Epheſus. Timothy an Evangeliſt. The prophecies that went before of him, and the grace he received. Titus and he over many Presbyteries. Biſhops over each af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. The Angels of the ſeven Churches.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>BUt as the Apoſtles began to wear out, or otherwiſe as their occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons gave them not leave to attend in perſon upon the Churches of their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115813:19"/> care, reaſon required, if but in corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence to the ſtate of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that had hitherto reſted in ſome Apoſtle and the Presbyteries of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, there ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted ſome heads of theſe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Presbyters, to whom the name of Biſhops hath been appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated ever ſince: and certain it is, that during the time of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles inſtituted they were. This a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth extreme well with the charge and inſtructions of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to his Diſciples Timothy and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, over the Churches of Aſia and Crete: whom as all Eccleſiaſticall writers, after Euſebius, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be made Biſhops of Epheſus and Crete, ſo muſt we not fail to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve here, that this was not done till it was revealed to the Apoſtle that from thenceforth the Lord would imploy him in the Weſtern parts of the world. The buſineſſe is moſt an
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115813:20"/> end agreed upon on all hands: yet becauſe the obſervation is ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to this purpoſe, let me take leave to inlarge it by clearing the whole paſſage of the Apoſtles laſt voyage, from Epheſus, through Greece, and back again. Acts xix. 21. we reade at that time <hi>Paul reſolved by the Spirit, having paſſed through Macedonia and Achaia, to go to Jeruſalem, ſaying, When I have been there I must alſo ſee Rome.</hi> In 2. Cor. i. 15. he writeth to them, that he had formerly purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to go firſt to Corinth, thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Macedonia, from Macedonia to Corinth again, and of the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to be brought on the way for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea: <hi>When I then purpoſed this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>did I uſe lightneſſe? or what I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe do I purpoſe according to the fleſh, that with me there ſhould be yea, yea, and nay, nay?</hi> ſignifying, that not taking up his reſolutions upon humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, it was no lightneſſe in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115813:20"/> him to balk his intended purpoſe, to follow the direction of the holy Ghoſt, in going firſt through Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia, God having ſo ordered it, it ſeemeth, for the reaſon that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans was ſent from Epheſus about this time: From Epheſus it is plain it was ſent, though ſubſcribed from Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi, (for thoſe ſubſcriptions, it is well known are of no credit) by the ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations he ſendeth, 1. Cor. xvi. 19. from the Churches of Aſia, from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila and Priſcilla, which dwelt there, Acts xviii. 19. And after his firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution was changed, becauſe he ſaith 1. Cor. 16. 5. that he meant to <hi>paſſe through Macedonia.</hi> In the 2. Cor. ii. 12. the Apoſtle relating one paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of that voyage, not mentioned in the Acts, <hi>When I came to Troas,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, a doore being opened me of the Lord, I had no reſt in my ſpirit, becauſe I found not</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115813:21"/> 
               <hi>Titus my brother: but taking leave of them I departed thence into Macedonia.</hi> Titus he deſired to meet with, becauſe he deſired to hear from Corinth by him that was coming from thence, 2. Cor. vii. 6. for as he proteſteth 2. Cor. i. 23. it was to <hi>ſpare them that he came not yet to Corinth: not yet,</hi> as being directed by the Spirit to go firſt through Macedonia, and to ſpare them, that is, not to be ingaged to proceed rigorouſly againſt them, in caſe they gave not due reſpect to his former Epiſtle. From Macedonia he diſpatcheth Titus to Corinth again, about the buſineſſe ſpecified 2. Cor. viii. 6, 16. and it is moſt like, upon theſe circumſtances, that both thoſe Epiſtles were ſent by Titus, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſubſcriptions bear. To go on with the Apoſtle in this voyage, Acts xx. 2. we reade, that having gone over the parts of Macedonia, and given them much exhortation, he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115813:21"/> came into Greece, and there abode three months. In this journey, let me be bold to affirm, it was that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle put in at Crete, to preach the Goſpel there: the relation agreeth ſo well from point to point, that I will uſe no other words to perſwade it is true, but the coherence of it. From Epheſus then the Apoſtle part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at Pentecoſt, 1. Cor. xvi. 8. By the way at Troas he ſtayed not, but came ſtraight into Macedonia, 2. Cor. ii. 12, 13. From thence having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched Titus for Corinth, 2. Cor. viii. 6, 16. going by ſea for Greece, he putteth in at Crete, to preach the Goſpel there; and meeting with Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus (returned from Corinth) in this journey, leaveth him in Crete to conſtitute Presbyters in every Citie, and to finiſh thoſe things which he for the ſtrait of time was fain to leave undone: and thus his three months being ſpent in Greece, he found win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115813:22"/> at Corinth. There he had once thought to have wintered, 1. Cor. xvi. 6. and that the Corinthians ſhould bring him on his journey, which there he expreſſed not, but 2. Cor. i. 16. it is for Judea. But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the Jews laid wait for him as he returned into Syria by ſea, Acts xx. 3. he taketh a reſolution to winter at Nicopolis, whereof he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieth Titus, appointing him to meet him there at ſpring, Tit. iii. 12. This was a convenient <hi>rendez-vow</hi> for the Apoſtle, in the mean while, to preach the Goſpel in the parts of Epirus, as farre as Illyricum: which he purpoſed to do, when he writ to the Corinthians, 2. Cor. x. 16. that when his ſpirit was in quiet in regard of them, he had hope <hi>to preach the Goſpel in the parts beyond them;</hi> and which he affirmeth to have done, Rom. xv. 19. where he writeth that from Jeruſalem to Illyricum he had
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115813:22"/> fully preached the Goſpel of Chriſt. And therefore, with leave I ſuppoſe, the Epiſtle to the Romanes is rather to be dated from hence then from Corinth, as the ſubſcription goeth: for before this it could not be ſent; after this we find not that he returned to Corinth: From whence being new come, he might ſend commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations from Gaius his hoſt at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, Rom. xvi. 23. 1. Cor. i. 14. and by Phebe he might write, ſeeing him in paſſing by the coaſt of Epirus, from Corinth to Rome. When win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſpent, from Dyrrachium, the confines of Epirus, (where he had wintered at Nicopolis) and Illyricum (whither his doctrine was got) the journey by land was ſhort and good to Theſſalonica in Macedonia, by the great road in Strabo called <hi>via Egna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia;</hi> ſo that in good time, after the dayes of unleavened bread, he might ſail from Philippi, as we reade he did,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115813:23"/> Acts xx. 5. This for Titus. As for Timothy's caſe, thus we reade, 1. Tim. i. 3. <hi>I beſought thee to abide ſtill at Epheſus, when I went into Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia.</hi> The ſound of theſe words maketh Baronius believe that Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy was left with his charge at Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus upon the beginning of this voyage of the Apoſtle through Greece. And he had Theodoret to go before him in the conceit: For in his Preface to S. Pauls Epiſtles he concludeth that the firſt Epiſtle to Timothy was ſent from Macedonia, when the Apoſtle paſſed through it. But it is eaſie to perceive that this cannot ſtand with the Scriptures. He that ſent Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus and Eraſtus before him into Macedonia Acts xx. 19. how could he leave him Biſhop at Epheſus? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, in the firſt Epiſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, iv. 17. xvi. 10. it is plain, that he was then ſending Timothy to Corinth, though he overtook him
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115813:23"/> before he got thither, in Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia: for afterwards Timothy was with him in Macedonia at the ſending of his ſecond Epiſtle to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, as appeareth by the beginning of it; and with him he was at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into Aſia through Macedonia, Acts xx. 4. It remaineth then that the Apoſtle coming through Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia to go into Aſia, began then to move Timothy to ſtay at Epheſus, 1. Tim. i. 3. and to take upon him the charge of the Churches of Aſia. Which being accordingly agreed and done, he ſendeth him before with the reſt of his company into Aſia, as we reade Acts xx. 4, 5. not knowing then how ſoon himſelf ſhould follow them: For thus he writeth, 1. Tim. iii. 14, 15. <hi>Theſe things write I unto thee, hoping to come unto thee ſhortly: but if I ſtay, that thou mayest know how to behave thy ſelf in the houſe of God.</hi> Therefore it is plain, that he ſendeth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115813:24"/> him this Epiſtle of inſtructions after their parting from Macedonia, but before his coming to Epheſus, it ſeemeth, while he ſtayed for him at Troas, as we reade Acts xx. 15. And thus we may well underſtand the words of Athanaſius <hi>in Synopſi,</hi> (though Baronius alledge him for his purpoſe) becauſe he ſaith no more but this, that the Firſt to Timothy was ſent from Macedonia. But the Apoſtle having reſolved, if it were poſſible, to be at Jeruſalem the day of Pentecoſt, Acts xx. 16. maketh haſt, and overtaketh his company at Troas, Acts xx. 6. And thus we ſee the reaſon why there is no reſpect of Timothy in his inſtructions to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Epheſus, Acts xx. 18. becauſe that then he began to enter upon his charge there, and becauſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions he had received from the Apoſtle by his firſt Epiſtle, beſides word of mouth. So the upſhot of all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115813:24"/> this diſcourſe is thus much, That within compaſſe of the time of this voyage, at the beginning whereof the Apoſtle ſaid in the Spirit, that <hi>when he had been at Jeruſalem he muſt alſo ſee Rome,</hi> Acts xix. 21. at the midſt whereof he writeth to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, chap. xv. 23. that <hi>he had no more place in thoſe parts,</hi> and at the end whereof he ſaith to the Elders of Epheſus, Acts xx. 25. <hi>And now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I know that all you among whom I have gone preaching the kingdome of God, ſhall ſee my face no more:</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by revelation that he was to ſerve God no more in thoſe parts, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his two Diſciples Timothy and Titus to be in his ſtead over the Churches of Aſia and Crete. Now that the charge of Timothy and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus giveth them a power as great as that of Biſhops was from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, no queſtion is made: if they prove not more then ſo, the buſineſſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115813:25"/> is clear. For true it is, ſomething not ordinary in Biſhops we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in Timothie's perſon, when he is called an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> 2. Tim. iv. 5. <hi>Do the work of an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt.</hi> To which we muſt referre that grace whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 1. Tim. iv. 14. <hi>Neglect not the gift that is in thee, that was given thee by prophecy, with the laying-on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi> Whereof again 2 Tim. i. 16. <hi>I put thee in mind that thou ſtirre up the gift that is in thee, by the putting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my hands:</hi> And 1. Tim. i. 18. <hi>This charge I commit unto thee, ſonne Timothy, according to the prophecies that went afore of thee.</hi> In this the Diſciples caſe is ſomewhat like the Apoſtles, as you ſhall ſee it anon, Acts xiii. 2. where the Prophets in the Church of Antiochia, having foretold through the holy Ghoſt what God would do in the planting of his Goſpel by his hands and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115813:25"/> and declared his will for ſetting them apart for that purpoſe, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they receive impoſition of hands: So likewiſe we muſt conceive that theſe prophecies went afore of Timothy, to inform the Church of the will of God concerning him, and the work he had appointed him to perform. As for the grace he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth by impoſition of hands, what other can any man imagine it to be then that which is deſigned in the name of an Evangeliſt, which the Apoſtle meant when he ſaid, Epheſ. iv. 11. that our Lord hath <hi>given</hi> to his Church, <hi>ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangelists?</hi> Or how can we further diſtinguiſh it otherwiſe from the gifts of Apoſtles and Prophets, then placing it in the extraordinary temporary indowments of the holy Ghoſt, inabling ſuch perſons, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the exigence of that time, to publiſh the Goſpel and to perſwade
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115813:26"/> it? which nevertheleſſe cometh ſhort of the perſonall qualitie of witneſſes of our Lord and his doctrine, and of the meaſure and kind of thoſe graces of miracles, languages, and the like, that make an Apoſtle. But he that would draw this into conſequence, and argue that Timothy was no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, becauſe an Evangeliſt, may with more reaſon conclude that Philip was no Deacon becauſe he was an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, and contradict the Scripture that ſaith Acts xxi. 8. <hi>We entred into the houſe of Philip the Evangeliſt, which was one of the ſeven.</hi> For if an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, in that eminence of graces and priviledges, nevertheleſſe abiding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a certain charge, and taking care of it, is to be counted Biſhop of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular place, as was argued afore, much more may an Evangeliſt for his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gift be a Biſhop for his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall charge: which is to ſay thus much in Engliſh, That the gift of an
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115813:26"/> Evangeliſt may fall upon any rank of ordinary Miniſters: as we ſee Philip, for his place in the Church one of the ſeven Deacons at Jeruſalem, Acts vi. 5. is nevertheleſſe an Evangeliſt for the graces God had beſtowed upon him, by his means to convert Samaria to the faith, Acts viii. 15. Nay further, if the gift of an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt be competible with a Deacons place, it muſt be granted that Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as an Evangeliſt is no Governour of Churches. And whereas it is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, that it was but a Commiſſion for the time which Timothy and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus are truſted with from the Apoſtle, becauſe it appeareth they were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles imployed otherwhere by the Apoſtle 2. Tim. iv. 9, 10. (as any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in caſe of publick neceſſities of the Church muſt be without the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) let me be bold to affirm, that the rules of continued ſettled govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, directed to them by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115813:27"/> to be executed by them in their perſons, are ſufficient evidence that they were appointed by him for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Governours, and not for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary Commiſſaries. Indeed as there is ſomething more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in Timothie's perſon, ſo is there ſomething more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Titus his charge, in that he was <hi>left in Crete, to ordain Presbyters in every citie,</hi> Tit. i. 5. by which, as appeareth in the ſequele of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, the Churches of thoſe cities were to be governed under Titus, as was obſerved afore. The like to be ſaid of Timothy, whoſe inſtructions, qualifying Presbyters and Deacons alone, leave him alone ſuperiour to all the Presbyteries he ſhould inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute according to his inſtructions. Now if we obſerved the cuſtome of the Apoſtles, hitherto ſet forth, of inſtituting Presbyteries in populous cities, and obſerve the cuſtome of the Church after their time, wherein
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115813:27"/> a Biſhop was alwayes head of one of theſe Presbyteries, <hi>(Quid eſt enim E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus niſi primus Presbyterorum?</hi> ſaith S. Auguſtine) it will not be hard to eſpy a difference between the place of a Biſhop and the extent of their charge. For it will not ſerve the turn to ſay, as ſome do, that Titus was Archbiſhop of Crete, and ſo intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with divers Churches: For an Archbiſhop is a chief among Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, not a perſon to govern divers Churches, ſeats of Biſhopricks. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, theſe degrees among Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops came in afterwards, when the Church became incorporate into the State of the Romane Empire, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the charge of Churches in head-Cities of Provinces, or according to the precedence of places, wherein the Emperours or chief temporall Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers made their reſidence. But in the mean time let me uſe Epiphanius his words, <hi>The Apoſtles could not ſettle all things uniformly at once.</hi> Is it a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115813:28"/> thing to argue, that becauſe S. Paul taketh no order for the heads of theſe Presbyteries which were not yet made, therefore he did not intend there ſhould be any ſuch in the Church? Rather let me argue, that becauſe S. Paul left two of his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Diſciples in two principall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with charge to plant Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as there was means to propagate Churches, therefore he gave a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of that which theſe Diſciples and all the Church was to do after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in ſettling the government of thoſe Churches, in the Presbyteries of them, and in their heads, which themſelves were for the time. And this we ſhall find was done in good time, in the Churches of Timothies charge, if we take but a ſhort conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the beloved Diſciple John the Apoſtle and Evangeliſt, what we find concerning him in Scriptures, or otherwiſe received and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115813:28"/> credible in this nature. He lived long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all the Diſciples, as is ſaid: and he will eaſily ſhew us Biſhops over the Churches of Timothies charge: for ſuch without doubt were the ſeven Churches of Aſia, unto whom the Apoſtle ſending from our Lord ſeven Epiſtles, ii. and iii. chapt. of his Revelation, directeth them to the <hi>Angels</hi> of thoſe Churches; a ſtyle not competible to a perſon of common rank, and the act of direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Epiſtles to one in the name and behalf of the whole Church, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing the eminence of the head, fit to anſwer for the body he repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Herewith agree the words of Clemens Alexandrinus in Euſebius, iii. 23. concerning this Apoſtle, that being returned from Patmus to Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, he uſed upon requeſt to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the neighbour-nations, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115813:29"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is, <hi>in ſome places to conſtitute Biſhops</hi> (to wit, where there were Presbyteries afore that yet had none) <hi>in ſome to found whole Churches, in others to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain a Clergie out of ſuch as were ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Spirit,</hi> as we reade of S. Paul and Timotheus. For will you have theſe to be Biſhops, according to the uſe of the word in S. Paul, where it is all one with Presbyters? Sure we muſt needs think of ſuch as his own writings make Angels of Churches. Ignatius, that was his Diſciple according to ſome, in all his Epiſtles ſpecifieth, and ſometimes by name, the Biſhops of ſome the ſame Churches, and ſome of others, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their Presbyteries; and in particular, Oneſimus, Timothie's ſucceſſour at Epheſus. Tertullian and Ireneus, the moſt ancient we can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, have named Polycarpus in particular, made Biſhop of Smyrna
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115813:29"/> by this Apoſtle. It is not poſſible to ſay more in this caſe. So often as we find mention of government in particular Churches in Scripture, ſo often we meet with Presbyteries, or the heads of Presbyteries, Apoſtles themſelves, or deriving their charge from the Apoſtles. Nay, it is very much, not pretending that Biſhops came on otherwiſe then to be in ſtead of the Apoſtles over particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches, that there is ſo much to be ſaid for their office out of Scriptures, all written during their time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115813:30"/>
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Presbyterie at Antiochia. S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and S. Paul heads of the Church there: Likewiſe of that at Rome. The difference about their next Succeſſours. Epiphanius his conjecture upon it. Another. Clemens ſucceeded S. Peter, and Linus S. Paul. The ſucceſsion of the Apoſtles there is unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe Church of Antiochia is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred next to that of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, in the Acts of the Apoſtles, but of the government thereof we have nothing ſo diſtinct or expreſſe in Scripture. Yet this we reade Acts xiii. 2. <hi>Now there were in the Church at Antiochia certain prophets and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. And as they miniſtred unto the Lord and fasted, the holy Ghoſt ſaid, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them.</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115813:30"/> 
               <hi>And when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away.</hi> That theſe Prophets and Teachers were all of them Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that Church, is more then can be affirmed, becauſe it is nowhere ſet down: But when we reade that they <hi>miniſtred unto the Lord</hi> (which muſt be underſtood of the ſervice of God in their aſſemblies, eſpecially in celebrating the Euchariſt) and gave <hi>impoſition of hands,</hi> we find among the number of them the works of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters, when there was no higher rank then that of Presbyters able to do the like. For as concerning the Heads of this Church, we muſt have recourſe to Ignatius his Epiſtle <hi>ad Magn.</hi> where he uſeth theſe words; <hi>For at Antiochia the Diſciples were first called Chriſtians, Paul and Peter found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church.</hi> And in the Epiſtle <hi>ad Antioch.</hi> (if it be his, as the other unqueſtionably is) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115813:31"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is, <hi>Ye are Pauls and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Diſciples. Remember Euodius, that first had the rule of you put into his hands by the Apostles.</hi> Be he what he will be that writ this, let me be bold to ſay, it agreeth marvellous well with what hath been ſaid, and with the Scripture: In which it is plain there were at the beginning two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of Chriſtians at Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia, one of the Circumciſion, the other converted from the Gentiles: becauſe S. Peter, Gal. ii. 12. fearing thoſe of the Circumciſion, withdrew himſelf, and ate no more with the Gentiles. In regard of the care of which two congregations, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by S. Peter and S. Paul, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diviſion agreed upon Gal. ii. 9. the words of Ignatius are to be verified, where he maketh both Apoſtles founders of the Church at
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115813:31"/> Antiochia. Who finding themſelves imployed in other parts of the world, took the ſame courſe with this Church which S. Paul did with thoſe he commended to Timothy and Titus, and put both congregations (by that time united and concorporate in one) under the charge of Euodius, prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour to Ignatius. Theſe two Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles are uſually counted founders of the Church at Rome, as well as of that of Antiochia. Ireneus, <hi>iii.</hi> 3. <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantes itaque &amp; instituentes beati Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoli Eccleſiam, Lino Epiſcopatum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae adminiſtrandae tradiderunt. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Lini Paulus in iis quae ſunt ad Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheum Epiſtolis meminit. Succedit autem ei Anacletus: Poſt eum tertio lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co ab Apoſtolis Epiſcopatum ſortitur Clemens.</hi> Where you ſee he referreth the foundation of that Church to both the Apoſtles, as doth Dionyſius alſo of Corinth ſome hundred and twentie years after their death, in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115813:32"/> Euſebius, <hi>Eccleſ. hist. iii.</hi> 26. and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of later ſtamp ſans number. Whereupon Epiphanius, <hi>Haer.</hi> 27. reckoning the ſucceſſion of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome, putteth Peter and Paul in the firſt place. But yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve further the difference between the words of Ireneus (which put Linus after the Apoſtles) and the Latine Church, which according to S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, <hi>Catal. Script. in</hi> CLEM. recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Clemens in that place: which Tertullian, the moſt ancient of that language, <hi>lib. De Praeſcript.</hi> averreth. To which difference we may aſcribe the confuſion that Baronius hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Pontificall book under the name of Pope Damaſus, an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent piece, but pieced indeed out of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall writings, and croſſe to one another divers times: As for the purpoſe; when it maketh Linus to ſucceed the Apoſtles, and ſuffer mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome the ſame year (who never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115813:32"/> ſitteth twelve years accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Euſebius) whereas Cletus, next in order unto him, beginneth ſeven years after in time, but Clemens, third in rank, one yeare after Linus, ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the third year of Trajane, long after both their deaths. Epiphanius in the place afore-named, ſtumbling, as it ſeemeth, at the credit of thoſe that put Clemens firſt, propoundeth this conjecture, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Theſe words of Clemens, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Epiphanins, are yet extant in his Epiſtle to the Church of Corinth, publiſhed not long ſince: wherein he telleth him that was the occaſion of the ſchiſme he writeth againſt there, that a generous man, and ſo forth, would ſay in that caſe, <hi>I depart; I</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115813:33"/> 
               <hi>withdraw: let the people of God be in quiet.</hi> Epiphanius, it ſeemeth, meeting them at the ſecond hand, alledged for Clemens his advice to ſome man mentioned in the Epiſtle, (as they are indeed) conceived nevertheleſſe they might have reference to his own caſe, adviſing to withdraw, and give way to Linus and Cletus, for the quiet of the Church: which now, by reading the Epiſtle, proveth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Beſides he ſticketh not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the inconvenience of admitting more then one Biſhop in the ſame Church at once. For becauſe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his conjecture, Linus and Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus as well as Clemens (that gave way to them) muſt be made Biſhops by the Apoſtles, he addeth, that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops might be made there during the time of the Apoſtles, becauſe they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled ſometimes from Rome, (S. Paul into Spain, as indeed he purpoſeth, Rom. xv. 24. S. Peter into Pontus
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115813:33"/> and Bithynia, whither he directeth his firſt Epiſtle) and muſt not leave the Church unprovided there. But if it be worth the while to vent a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture that ſhall avoid this inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, and make all good that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by theſe ancient Fathers, that matters of circumſtance wherein they are at difference deſtroy not their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the main wherein they are at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; let this be mine; That there were at Rome from the beginning, as at Antiochia two congregations of Chriſtians, one of the Circumciſion, the other of the Gentiles; That S. Peter was head of the one, S. Paul of the other, according to the diviſion aforeſaid; That after their death, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, who was Deacon to S. Paul, if we believe Ignatius in the Epiſtle to the Trallians, ſucceeded him over the one; Clemens, who was Deacon to S. Peter, according to the ſame Authour there, ſucceeded him over
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115813:34"/> the other, till both Congregations being concorporate and united in one, becauſe governed by Clemens, that ſurvived. And if any man be ſo disfavourable as upon theſe differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the By to diſcredit the main, let him know, that though he allow not the pillars of the Church in their time the credit of diſcreet men, to have reaſon for what they report, yet muſt he allow Ireneus and Tertullian to be men of common ſenſe, when they alledge the ſucceſſion of Biſhops in the Churches of that time, wherein that of Rome is alwayes one, for an evidence of the faith which had been preſerved in them ever ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: the force of the reaſon lying in that, which Calvine hath exceeding well obſerved, That it was a thing known and received at that time, that <hi>de facto</hi> the faith which the Churches profeſſed came by ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles, from which ſucceſſion
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115813:34"/> the Hereticks were fain to ſeparate, and make Congregations apart, wherein to profeſſe the belief which themſelves had deviſed. Be all the world judges now, whether a man in his right ſenſes would appeal to the ſucceſſion of Biſhops, if it had been a thing queſtionable whether any ſuch were or not. The like is to be ſaid of Optatus and S. Auguſtine, when they appeal to the ſucceſſion of Biſhops in the Church of Rome to prove the Donatiſts ſchiſmaticks, not communicating with the lawfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours both of the faith of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which both ſides granted, and of their places, from which they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115813:35"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius the Areopagite Biſhop of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. S. Mark of Alexandria. No Biſhop at Corinth, when Clemens writ his Epiſtle. How they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated, and by what rule.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THus we are out of the Scripture: But becauſe we are not yet out of the time of the Apoſtles, I will name further Dionyſius the Areopagite, S. Pauls convert, Acts xvii. 34. becauſe there is ſo ancient a witneſſe to depoſe for him, Dionyſius of Corinth, ſome hundred and twenty years after that, averring in Euſebius that he was the firſt Biſhop of Athens. And ſo the laſt I will name ſhall be the Church of Alexandria, and that for S. Hieromes ſake, and in his words, becauſe he it is that is perſwaded, and perſwadeth men to think, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Biſhops came in by mere cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115813:35"/> of the Church, to avoid ſchiſmes that ariſe for want of heads. In his Epiſtle to Euagrius thus we reade, <hi>Nam &amp; Alexandriae à Marco Evangelista uſque ad Heraclam &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſium Epiſcopos, Presbyteri ſemper unum ex ſe electum in excelſiori gradu collocatum Epiſcopum nominabant.</hi> How that can be ſaid to come in by cuſtome for avoyding of ſchiſme, which was practiced at Alexandria from Mark the Evangeliſt, let S. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erome deviſe: it ſhall ſerve our turn, that ſo it was there from the Apoſtles time. Otherwiſe it is reaſonable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to believe that upon ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions Biſhops came in over ſome Churches, in particular the Church of Corinth, in which we find a ſchiſme, but can find no Biſhop at the time of writing Clemens his Epiſtle, ſome few years after the death of the Apoſtles: Becauſe the reaſon produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced afore to argue that there was no
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115813:36"/> Biſhop at Corinth when S. Paul writ his Epiſtles, continueth ſtill in force at the time of writing Clemens his Epiſtle. For <hi>p.</hi> 52. he is very earneſt with them to keep due order and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum</hi> in bringing their Oblations and celebrating the Euchariſt: For when he nameth there <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the one we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſpecies of fruits of the earth, and meats, which the people offered, out of which the Euchariſt being ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated, the reſt was ſpent in the <hi>Agapa,</hi> or feaſt of Love; to which the words of the Apoſtle are to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: By the other, the Euchariſt, for celebration whereof he is ſo earneſt with them to keep due order in their aſſemblies; alledging that theſe things which the Lord had commanded to be done, theſe he had not command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be done diſorderly and at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but at ſet times and ſeaſons, when and by whom they ſhould be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115813:36"/> done. Where God hath appointed an order, when and where and by whom Chriſtians ſhould celebrate their aſſemblies, is not to be found in Scripture further then the Apoſtles rule, 1. Cor. xiv. 40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi> It ſeemeth he argueth from the pattern of the Leviticall Prieſthood: for ſo it followeth, <hi>p.</hi> 53. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>To the high Prieſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are aſsigned his proper ſervices.</hi> Which further appeareth, when he urgeth the example of their ſacrifices that were offered before the Temple, being firſt viſited <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 54. But the Presbyters of that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church he exhorteth with theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>let every one of you give thanks to God</hi> (that is,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115813:37"/> 
               <hi>Celebrate the Euchariſt,</hi> in his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) <hi>in his own order, being in a good conſcience, not ſtepping out of the ſet rule of his Miniſtery.</hi> Perhaps his meaning is, that they ſhould celebrate by turns. Howſoever here is my reaſon that there was then no Biſhop there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then there could not have been ſo much debate about the order in celebrating the aſſemblies of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which, as ſhall be ſhewed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, were not to be held but upon appointment of the Biſhop, with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Presbyters, being a mark of ſchiſme to aſſemble otherwiſe. And if this be not enough, there is another to ſecond it. Whatſoever may be argued from the diſſenſions at Corinth, one ſaying, <hi>I am of Paul,</hi> another, <hi>I am of Cephas,</hi> to ſhew that there was no Biſhop there when the Apoſtle writ this, and in his abſence, ſtill continueth in force at the time of writing Clemens his Epiſtle: The
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115813:37"/> whole ſubject whereof is, to quell ſuch another diſſenſion as this, but onely that it was not under ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable names, of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Cephas</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> as he complaineth, but (which is remarkable to prove my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) was (as he ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 62.) a mere faction, for the love of one or two perſons, againſt the Presbyters; no Biſhop bearing any part either at one end or other of it. Neither is it mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel that this Church ſhould be ſtill without a Biſhop for ſome ten or twentie years perhaps after the death of the Apoſtle, ſo many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of the Apoſtles being then alive, Clemens at Rome, Titus in Crete, Timothy at Epheſus, Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius at Athens, others elſewhere, to furniſh whatſoever aſſiſtance they had received from the Apoſtle during his time, no otherwiſe then did Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and Titus to thoſe Churches wherein they had planted Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115813:38"/> before they had Biſhops. And this muſt be the anſwer, if any man ask the queſtion how Biſhops came to be propagated through all Churches; the anſwer muſt be, They were made in due time by the heads of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Churches: which we ſhall diſcern anon, when we come to ſpeak of the courſe held from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in the choice and conſtitution of Biſhops. And by the practice of the Church it ſhould ſeem the aim was afarre off to propagate Biſhops according to the firſt practice of the Apoſtles. For as they planted Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries to govern Mother-Churches in Mother-Cities, ſo when it became queſtionable, which Churches ſhould have Biſhops and which not, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was regulated according to the greatneſſe of Cities, or the multitude of Presbyters which the ſervice of the Churches in them required, whereof the Biſhops were to be heads. And
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115813:38"/> therefore in the Councel of Sardica <hi>Can. vi.</hi> it is provided, that there ſhould be no Biſhop in towns or ſmall cities where one Presbyter might ſerve; but in thoſe places where Biſhops were of old time, or if a place became ſo populous that it might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to have a Biſhop; that is, either in Cities that had been ſo populous of old time as to have Biſhops, or which ſhould afterwards become ſo populous. But the xvii. Can on of the Chalcedon Councel providing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt innovation in Dioceſes, taketh order nevertheleſſe, that when a place is promoted by the Emperour to be a Citie, the form of the Church ſhall go along with the form of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, that is, it ſhall have a Biſhop, and his Dioceſe the territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that Citie. There is here a difference in the particular, and yet the ſame generall ground of both Canons, the practice of the Apoſtles,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115813:39"/> ordaining Presbyteries to govern the Churches which they had planted in Cities, the heads whereof were Biſhops after their departure. And this ſeemeth to be the reaſon why the ſeats of Cathedrall Churches are wont to be Cities. And by this means Italy is ſo full of Biſhopricks, becauſe it is ſo full of Cities.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Presbyters govern with the Apoſtles in Scriptures. Nothing done in the Church without their adviſe. Why both ranks are called</hi> Sacerdotes, Presbyteri, Antiſtites, <hi>and the like.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>HAving hitherto juſtified the ground whereupon we go, and ſhewed that Biſhops came after the Apoſtles to be heads of Presbyteries, in conſequence hereunto it muſt now be averred, that the government of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115813:39"/> Churches paſſed in common by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyters, as from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the Presbyters governed with the Apoſtles themſelves. If in that great action of the Councel at Jeruſalem the Elders of that Church bore their part with the Apoſtles, what cauſe have we to think they did leſſe when they were diſperſed, S. James alone remaining there? If they concurred with S. James in his adviſe to S. Paul about a matter of greateſt weight, how to deal with thoſe of the Circumciſion that believed, ſhall we imagine they did not do the like with his ſucceſſours? If S. Peter call the Presbyters of the Churches to which he writeth his <hi>fellow-Elders,</hi> it is to the purpoſe to put them in mind of their ſhare in that office which he chargeth himſelf with. If the Apoſtle of the Gentiles charge the Elders of the Church of Epheſus, Acts xx. 18. with their part of that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115813:40"/> care of Chriſts flock after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which he for his time had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed over them, ſhall we think them eaſed of it becauſe Timothy came to be Biſhop there? Rather let me conceive this to be the cauſe why Timothie's inſtructions are addreſſed in the ſingular number to him alone, without mention of his Presbyters, becauſe they were to receive their charge by themſelves about the ſame time: So farre is it from me to think that his Presbyters were not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in aſſiſting that courſe of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment wherein he alone is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Apoſtle to proceed. And if we can go no further in proving this point out of Scripture, the reaſon muſt be, becauſe (as appeareth by that which hath been ſaid) the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures for the moſt part ſpeak of that time when Biſhops yet were not, but the Apoſtles themſelves. To which purpoſe nevertheleſſe there will be
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115813:40"/> ſtill ſomething to be ſaid out of the Scriptures, in the particulars which we ſhall ſurvey. In the mean time let us take notice of a few paſſages, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many more, out of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call writers, to argue the generall whereof we ſpeak. Ignatius, <hi>Epiſt. ad Trall.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand righter what the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery meaneth, then out of theſe words, a Colledge or bench of Aſſeſſours to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in ſacred matters.</hi> The Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries under S. Ambroſe his name upon 1. Tim. v. 1. ſpeak home to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <hi>Nam apud omnes utique gentes honorabilis eſt ſenectus: unde &amp; Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga, &amp; postea Eccleſia, Seniores habuit, ſine quorum conſilio nihil agebatur in Eccleſia.</hi> This is as much as can be demanded, when we heare that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was done in the Church, to wit by the Biſhop, without the advice of his Presbyters. The ſame is affirmed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115813:41"/> by S. Hierome upon Titus i. 5. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequam Diaboli inſtinctu ſtudia in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione fierent, &amp; diceretur in populis, Ego ſum Pauli, ego Apollo, ego Cephae, communi conſilio Eccleſiae gubernaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> In that S. Hierome thinketh there were no Biſhops till Churches were forced to that courſe to avoid ſchiſmes, it hath been ſhewed he is not in the right: But in that he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that at firſt Churches were governed by common adviſe, we may well heare him ſpeak in ſo good company of witneſſes. Laſt of all, S. Cyprian having ſaid once for all, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6. <hi>Quando à primordio Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patûs mei nihil ſtatuerim ſine conſilio veſtro [Presbyterorum &amp; Diaconorum] &amp; ſine conſenſu plebis meae, privatá ſententiâ gerere,</hi> how well he obſerved it, is yet to be ſeen in the paſſage of divers buſineſſes related in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. Out of which the like is to be conceived of the Presbyters of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115813:41"/> Rome, by thoſe things that are touched there. And this is the true reaſon why many times (eſpecially among the moſt ancient Church-writers) Biſhop and Presbyters both are compriſed in the ſame ſtyles and names, not becauſe there were then no Biſhops (as ſome men imagine) but becauſe both States concurred in the ſame office. Clemens in the Epiſtle aforeſaid, pag. 54. ſpeaking of the Miniſteries inſtituted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſaith thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That is, <hi>They made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the firſt-fruits of believers Overſeers and Miniſters</hi> (that is, <hi>Biſhops and Deacons) of thoſe that ſhould believe.</hi> It ſeemeth indeed that Clemens calleth the Presbyters Biſhops, becauſe as yet there was no other Biſhop there, as was proved afore: for ſo the word is uſed in S. Pauls Epiſtles and the Acts of the Apoſtles, for the ſame reaſons, as hath
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115813:42"/> been ſaid. But in Ignatius his Epiſtle to Hero his Deacon at Antiochia you have theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Do nothing without the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops;</hi> that is, <hi>without the Presbyters:</hi> who were indeed Biſhops in Ignatius his abſence, when this is pretended to be written. And be he who he will be that writ it, I believe it will not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten be found that Presbyters are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Biſhops in any monument of Church-writers after this time, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be in theſe words of Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>De praeſcript. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Quid ergò ſi E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus, ſi Diaconus, ſi vidua,</hi> &amp;c? where putting the Deacon next to the Biſhop, he ſeemeth to compriſe the Presbyter with him in the ſame ſtyle: For afterwards the name of Biſhops became appropriate to the heads of Presbyteries: as we heard S. Hierome ſay of the Presbyters at A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria, that the head whom they
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115813:42"/> choſe themſelves out of their own number, they named BISHOP of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria. Otherwiſe, as it is well known that the name of SACERDOS is common to both eſtates, in regard of the offices of Divine ſervice which were performed by both, ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the government of the Church, common to both, are they many times compriſed together in the common ſtyle of PRESBYTERS, the name of their age, or ANTISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, PRAEPOSITI, and the like, the names of their charge. For as the Apoſtle maketh himſelf an Elder, when he writeth to them in this ſtyle, 1. Pet. i. 5. <hi>The Elders I exhort, who am alſo an Elder;</hi> ſo is the like to be obſerved in that well-known paſſage of Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus related by Euſebius, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hiſt. iii.</hi> 23. concerning the youth which S. John the Apoſtle commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Biſhop of a certain place,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115813:43"/> Clemens proceeding in the relation addeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>But the Elder,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>taking the youth home to his houſe,</hi> &amp;c. calling him a <hi>Presbyter</hi> whom he had named a <hi>Biſhop</hi> but juſt afore. So Tertullian, <hi>Apologet. c.</hi> 39. deſcribing what was wont to be done in the Aſſemblies of Chriſtians, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>Praeſident probati quique Senio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, honorem non pretio ſed teſtimonio adepti;</hi> not meaning to tell us that there was no Biſhop to be ſeen at theſe meetings, (for in his book <hi>De praeſcript.</hi> where he nameth Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, whom we alledged afore, <hi>cap.</hi> 32. Biſhop of Smyrna, he ſpeaketh as much of Biſhops that ſucceded the Apoſtles in the reſt of the Churches of their planting) but compriſing both ranks and eſtates in one name of ELDERS: And that upon the reaſon ſpecified in the Commentaries under S. Ambroſe his name, upon 1. Tim. iii. 8. where he giveth the reaſon why
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115813:43"/> the Apoſtle paſſeth ſtraight from Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to Deacons; Becauſe, ſaith he, every Biſhop is a Presbyter, though every Presbyter is not a Biſhop, who is the chief of Presbyters. And the true S. Ambroſe <hi>Offic. i.</hi> 20. <hi>Viduarum &amp; virginum domos, niſi viſitandi gratiâ juniores adire non eſt opus: &amp; hoc cum Senioribus, hoc eſt, cum Epiſcopo, vel ſi opus eſt, cum Presbyteris,</hi> With the Elders, ſaith he, that is, with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Presbyters. Juſtine Martyr in his ſecond Apology relating the orders of Chriſtians in their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, having ſpoken of reading the Scriptures, <hi>Then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Reader having done,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Ruler, maketh a ſpeech of instruction to the people, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them to imitate what was read.</hi> And again of the Euchariſt, <hi>Then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>bread and wine is offered to the Ruler,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Was it the Biſhop alone, or the Presbyters alone, that preached, and celebrated the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt?
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115813:44"/> Sure both did it, and the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was choſen on purpoſe by Juſtine to compriſe both. The ſame is to be obſerved in the words of S. Auguſtine <hi>Hom. ult. ex quinquaginta, cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Veniat peccator ad Antiſtites, per quos illi in Eccleſia claves miniſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; à Praepoſitis ſacrorum accipiat ſatisfactionis ſuae modum.</hi> ANTISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES <hi>in Eccleſia</hi> is not the Biſhop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but the Biſhop and the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Hegeſippus in Euſebius, <hi>Eccleſ. hiſt. iii.</hi> 20. relateth how ſome of our Lords kindred were brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Domitian upon ſuſpicion of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the State in regard of their title to the Kingdome, but diſmiſſed by him upon notice of their profeſſion of life, in tilling their grounds with their own hands, tried by the hardneſſe of them which it had wrought. <hi>Theſe,</hi> ſaith Hegeſippus, <hi>were hereupon choſen</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to be leaders of Churches, as both Couſins of our Lord,</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:115813:44"/> 
               <hi>and his witneſſes,</hi> comprehending both Biſhop and Presbyters in one title. As in Ignatius, <hi>ad Trall.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is put in one word to expreſſe Biſhops and Presbyters both, as the circumſtance of the place will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. To this we muſt adde the words of Ireneus, iv. 43. <hi>Wherefore,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it behoveth us to obey the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that are in the Church, which have received according to the Fathers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the certain grace of truth, with the ſucceſsion of their Biſhoprick.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, iii. 3. he ſpeaketh of the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on coming from the Apoſtles, which had been preſerved in the Churches through the ſucceſſion of Presbyters. Ireneus, that is wont to appeal to the ſucceſſion of Biſhops, to evidence that which the Church then believed to have come from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, here referreth himſelf to the Presbyters for the ſame purpoſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that they ſucceeded the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115813:45"/> without doubt, calling the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops by the name of PRESBYTERS in regard of the office common to both. Thus are both ranks compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in one name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the firſt Canon of the Councel at Antiochia, where we reade, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Where we are not to conceive that Deacons are reckoned among the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as hath been miſtook; but the ſenſe is to be direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by diſtinguiſhing the words thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, reckoning the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as well Presbyters as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, neither more nor leſſe then ANTISTITES in Latine, which we had in S. Auguſtine before: And thus you have both ranks compriſed in the ſame ſtyle of PRAEPOSITI in S. Cyprian, and of PRAESIDEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES in Tertullian: The firſt, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 62. <hi>Et cùm omnes omnino diſciplinam tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115813:45"/> 
               <hi>oporteat, multò magis Praepoſitos &amp; Diaconos curare hoc fas eſt.</hi> The other, <hi>De Cor. mil. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Euchariſtiae Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum nec de aliorum manu quàm Praeſidentium ſumimus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>What pattern this Government might have in the Synagogue. Aaron and his ſonnes. Correſpondence of the Sanedrin with the Biſhop and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>BEfore we leave this point, it will not be amiſſe to take notice what pattern the Apoſtles might have for this form of government in the Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agogue. For when our Lord in the Goſpel, Matth. xviii. 17. giveth his Diſciples in the caſe of private offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the rule, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae,</hi> it is to be ſuppoſed he reflecteth upon ſome Bench to which that people were wont to reſort with their cauſes
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:115813:46"/> (otherwiſe what could the hearers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by theſe words?) intimating that his will was, the Church which he was now founding, to be provided of the like. Nevertheleſſe, in regard this Church was intended a mere ſpirituall State, to be cheriſhed and nouriſhed in the boſome and entrails as it were of all Common-wealths, there muſt no compariſon be made in that which concerneth the temporall ſtate of that people. Let us ſee then Moſes his charge: Deut. xvii. 8, 9. thus we reade, <hi>If there ariſe a matter too hard for thee in judgement between bloud and bloud, between plea and plea, between ſtroke and ſtroke, being mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of controverſie within thy gates; then ſhalt thou ariſe, and get thee up into the place which the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe, and thou ſhalt come unto the Priests and Levites, and to the Judges that ſhall be in thoſe dayes, and enquire, and they ſhall ſhew thee the ſentence of</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:115813:46"/> 
               <hi>judgement.</hi> He that readeth here on the one ſide two ſorts of perſons, <hi>the Prieſts and Levites</hi> for one, and <hi>the Judge that ſhall be in thoſe dayes;</hi> on the other ſide, two ſorts of cauſes, one concerning Ceremonies of the Religion in force, the other the civil Laws of that people; hath cauſe to think that the meaning of this law is, that they ſhould reſort to ſeverall perſons, according to the differences of their cauſes: Eſpecially, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in the words, to tranſlate it thus, <hi>Thou ſhalt come to the Prieſts, the Levites, or to the Judge that ſhall be in thoſe dayes,</hi> as after verſe 12. it is read. Had it been thus, the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence had been clear between the high Prieſt and his inferiours in the Synagogues, and the Biſhop and his Presbyters in the Church. But the practice of the Nation beareth it otherwiſe: In which we muſt believe their Doctours, when they tell us that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115813:47"/> the whole paſſage, as well that of <hi>the Prieſts and Levites</hi> as that of <hi>the Judge that ſhall be in thoſe dayes,</hi> is referred to the Sanedrin, whereof R. Iſaack Abartincell giveth his reaſon in his Commentaries upon that place, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Court for a great part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of Prieſts and Levites, and therefore had the hearing of all ſorts of cauſes. And though they were brought hither from lower Courts, (whereof there was one of three and twenty perſons in every place which conteined one hundred and twenty families, one of three in leſſe places) by the Judges themſelves, as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Doctours will have it, arguing from the words, THOU SHALT ARISE, <hi>Thou that findeſt a matter too hard for thee in judgement, ſhalt ariſe;</hi> yet can we compare the Conſiſtory of the Church with no Court but this. Firſt, becauſe all mother-Churches in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Cities are abſolute in their rule,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115813:47"/> ſo farre as the Scripture hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; otherwiſe then as the law of love tieth Chriſtians to aſſiſt one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others neceſſities: our Lord and his Apoſtles having inſtituted no other judicatories in ſpirituall matters, but one of theſe Presbyteries in each Church, and many of them in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Churches, when the matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired common adviſe. And again, becauſe Jeruſalem was the onely ſeat of the whole State of Religion and Juſtice both, in that people, ſacrifices being done no where elſe. Well then, as Ignatius in one of his Epiſtles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth two parts of the Biſhops office, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to rule the Church, and to perform Divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> ſo muſt we inquire the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency of the Church with the Synagogue in both reſpects: reflecting from the Biſhop and Presbyters, in regard of Divine ſervice to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by their hands, upon Aaron
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:115813:48"/> and his ſonnes, or the high Prieſt and the reſt, as S. Hierome hath done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, writing in theſe terms, <hi>Epiſt. ad Euagr. Quod Aaron &amp; filii ejus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Levitae in templo fuerunt, hoc ſibi Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopi &amp; Presbyteri &amp; Diaconi vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in Ecclesia.</hi> But in reſpect of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Diſcipline, whereof our Lord ſpeaketh in the Goſpel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, we muſt reflect upon the Sanedrin, as the ſame S. Hierome hath done in another place, upon the firſt to Titus, ſaying of Biſhops in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Presbyters, <hi>Imitantes Moyſen, qui cùm haberet in poteſtate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus praeeſſe populo Iſrael, ſeptuaginta elegit cum quibus populum judicaret.</hi> So then, Moſes his Spirit is taken and divided upon ſeventie Elders, to help him to bear the charge of the people, Num. xi. 25. The ſame thing is done when the Apoſtles ordain Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by impoſition of hands. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee the Spirit of Prophecy
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115813:48"/> reſt upon the Presbytery by which Timothy was ordained, as well as upon that of Antiochia, no otherwiſe then it did upon Moſes his Sanedrin, Num. xi. 26. To continue and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the continuance whereof upon their ſucceſſours, it was, that this Court ſate in the Temple, as the old Ebrew Doctours obſerve it is ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt go up to the place which I ſhall chooſe;</hi> ſignifying that the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in which the holy Ghoſt dwelt, occaſioned the influence of it upon the Court that ſate there. But when Moſes was dead, a Preſident was choſen over and beſide the ſeventy, whom they called the Naſi, to be in his ſtead from age to age, as R. Moſes writeth: ſuch is the Biſhop, chief of the Presbyters, after an Apoſtle. All the difference is this, The Sanedrin is but one, as the nation to which God was known was but one; whereas the Apoſtle and his ſucceſſours remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115813:49"/> head of ſo many Presbyteries as his office of preaching the Goſpel to all Nations adviſeth him to inſtitute, as hath been ſaid.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Presbyteries compoſed of no lay perſons, as the Sanedrin. What is brought out of the Scripture to that purpoſe. The labour of Presbyters in the Word and Doctrine. Preaching went by Gifts, under the Apoſtles. Thoſe Gifts make no different Miniſteries. Teaching and ruling belong to the ſame Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters. No colour for lay Elders in the Primitive Church. Preaching, how rightly esteemed.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>IT is well enough known, how this compariſon and the text that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioneth it is drawn into conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to prove that Presbyteries were intended to conſiſt part of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the people, part of Miniſters
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115813:49"/> of the Church, as the Sanedrin of ſome Prieſts and Levites, ſome of the people: And it is as well to be known, what a forced preſumption it is, to require correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church and the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue in that point which the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a mere Spirituall and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Common-wealth bringeth to paſſe. The Sanedrin conſiſted of the chief of that people as well as of Prieſts and Levites, becauſe the chief cauſes of that Common-wealth as well as of Religion paſſed through their hands: The Church is ſubject to all Common-wealths where it is mainteined, in temporall matters: In thoſe which concern the ſoul, whom ſhall we think our Lord leaveth her in charge with, but thoſe whom he truſteth with the keyes of his houſe? Who thoſe are we ſhall ſee anon: In the mean time let this ſerve their turn that will needs preſume that theſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115813:50"/> Presbyteries muſt conſiſt part of lay-perſons, as the Sanedrin; while we prove that <hi>de facto</hi> they did conſiſt of none but Miniſters of the Church: For upon this occaſion, it will not be amiſſe here to adde the utmoſt of the reſt whereupon that platform is grounded in Scripture: w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is in effect no more then that text of the Apoſtle 1. Tim. v. 17. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour, eſpecially thoſe that labour in the word and doctrine,</hi> carrying at the firſt ſound an appearance of two ſorts of Elders, ſome Preachers, others nothing but Rulers. It is ſeconded indeed by thoſe paſſages of the Apoſtles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they reckon the graces, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Church, diſtributed upon the members of it upon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion of Chriſt, Epheſ. iv. 4. <hi>ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, ſome Paſtours and Doctours;</hi> or elſe both for edification and for other
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115813:50"/> neceſſities, Rom. xii. 6. <hi>Prophecying, Miniſtring, Teaching, Exhorting, Communicating, Ruling;</hi> and 1. Cor. xii. 28. <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Teachers, Miracles, Gifts of Healing, Helps in Government, Tongues:</hi> and afore verſ. 8. thoſe gifts which are called <hi>the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the Spirit, given to every man to profit withall,</hi> becauſe of their uſe to the edification of the Church of that time, are reckoned as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>the word of Wiſdome, the word of Knowledge, Faith, gifts of Healing, Miracles, Prophecy, Diſcerning of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, Tongues, Interpretation of Tongues;</hi> and 1. Pet. iv. 11. <hi>Speaking,</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring.</hi> But that which is gathered hence, is but in conſequence to the two ſorts of Elders, ſuppoſed out of the Text aforeſaid. For out of theſe paſſages are culled the gifts of <hi>Ruling</hi> or <hi>Helps in Government,</hi> and <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring,</hi> the offices of <hi>Paſtours,</hi> of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> or <hi>Teachers;</hi> upon preſumption
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115813:51"/> of the difference aforeſaid, to argue, That the Miniſteries appointed to continue in the Church till our Lords coming to judgement, are, that of <hi>Paſtours,</hi> to preach in the Church; that of <hi>Rulers</hi> or <hi>Helps in the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Elders of the people, to aſſiſt in Ruling; and laſt of all <hi>Doctours</hi> or <hi>Teachers,</hi> to reade leſſons in point of Religion, not medling with Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; beſides <hi>Deacons,</hi> to whom the gift of <hi>Ministring</hi> belongeth. Here it is plain, there is work cut out: And ſure it is a fit place to take into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration the firſt part of that Office we pretend to prove common to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Presbyters, conſiſting in labour in the word and doctrine, as it was in the Primitive time, and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the Apoſtle: Which withall will make appear upon what ſort of perſons the Rule of the Church was eſtated. Without doubt, when we have named the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115813:51"/> of the true faith by preventing the creeping in of hereſies and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, the Inſtruction of thoſe that are converted in the myſteries of the faith, Diligence in propagating it by converting more and more, we have named a very great work of labour in the word and doctrine, and yet ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied nothing but that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the Presbyters office from the beginning. For when the Apoſtle Acts xx. 29. foretelleth to the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters of Epheſus <hi>the coming in of grievous wolves, that ſhould not ſpare the flock,</hi> and <hi>the riſing up of perverſe Teachers,</hi> it is to the purpoſe to put them in mind, (verſe 31) <hi>to be watchfull</hi> of theſe things, as of their own charge; vouching withall his own example verſ. 20. <hi>in preaching, and teaching them both in publick, and houſe by houſe, admoniſhing them with teares, every man in particular,</hi> as it followeth verſ. 31. for them in their place and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115813:52"/> rank to follow. And the rule of the Apoſtle, Gal. vi. 6. <hi>Let him that is catechized, communicate to him that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizeth in all good things,</hi> without doubt aimeth at this private way of inſtruction whereof we ſpeak. Be the ſame ſaid of the other Apoſtles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to his Elders, 1. Pet. v. 2. <hi>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by constraint but willingly, not for filthy lucre</hi> (becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>the Elders that rule well are counted worthy of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honour,</hi> that is, <hi>reward) but of a ready mind, neither as being Lords of Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the flock.</hi> And again, the office of Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the flock, by which the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church are charactered Heb. xiii. 17. the parts of a Biſhop in the inſtructions of Timothy and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, that concern Teaching and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing in the faith, as by the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words they may conſiſt, ſo
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:115813:52"/> for my part they are undoubtedly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to conſiſt moſt an end, for the time of the Apoſtles, in that private diligence, thoſe abilities, that watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, that Presbyters were to uſe in guiding and inſtructing particular perſons of Chriſtians, which in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence muſt be underſtood of that <hi>labour in the word and doctrine</hi> ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the leading Text, 1. Tim. v. 17. And the reaſon ſhall be, becauſe then, to the beſt of my judgement, (which if it prove otherwiſe, then ſhall the ſpirits of the Prophets be ſubject to the Prophets) the work of preaching in the aſſemblies of Chriſtians at that time, ſo farre as we underſtand by the Apoſtle, went more by mens gifts then by their places in the Church. Reade the fourteenth chapter of the firſt to the Corinthians throughout, and conſider what great uſe there was of the gifts of prophecying and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrange languages in their aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115813:53"/> which the Apoſtle there regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, ſure you will never imagine (for there is not a ſyllable to intimate it) that theſe were all Presbyters, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters in the Church. The like muſt be ſaid of the gifts recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, verſ. 8. <hi>The word of Wiſdome, the word of Knowledge, Diſcerning ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> and the like; of the gifts of <hi>Teaching</hi> and <hi>Exhorting,</hi> Rom. xii. 7, 8. of <hi>Paſtours</hi> and <hi>Doctours,</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the Apoſtle, Epheſ. iv. 14. The Office of the Presbyters at Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonica, the Apoſtle recommendeth to the brethren there in theſe terms, 1. Theſſ. 5. 12. <hi>We beſeech you, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to know them which labour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you: And to eſteem them very highly in love, for their works ſake.</hi> But we are not bound to think them all the ſame perſons whoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he recommendeth, when he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, verſ. 19. 20. <hi>Quench not the</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:115813:53"/> 
               <hi>Spirit: Deſpiſe not propheſying.</hi> Acts xiii. 1. There were in the Church of Antiochia <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Teachers:</hi> and of them they were that gave Paul and Barnabas <hi>impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands.</hi> And 1. Tim. iv. 14. theſe are thoſe that <hi>propheſied</hi> of him, and Presbyters they were, I ſuppoſe, that gave him <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> with the Apoſtle. And ſo it was argued from hence afore, that the Spirit of Propheſie reſted upon thoſe Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries. But that all ſuch Prophets were Presbyters, or all Presbyters ſuch Prophets, neither is it written in Gods book, nor of it ſelf credible, in ſuch varietie of graces ſpecified, which all being given for edification, and uſed in the aſſemblies to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, muſt either reſt in the rank of ordinary Miniſters, or be counted perſonall graces, whether miraculous or otherwiſe, uſed for the edification of the Church, in ſupplement of their
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115813:54"/> indeavours which have ſerved the turn in after ages. He that writ the Commentaries upon S. Pauls Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, under S. Ambroſe his name, upon Epheſ. iv. 10. having laboured to accommodate the gifts there ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the Miniſteries then in uſe in the Church, is at length driven to this point, <hi>Tamen poſtquam omnibus loci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſiae ſunt conſtitutae, &amp; officia ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata, aliter compoſita res eſt quàm coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat. Primùm enim omnes docebant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; omnes baptizabant, quibuſcunq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diebus vel temporibus fuiſſet occaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> And after a while, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ergò creſcere plebs &amp; multiplicaretur, omnibus int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> initia conceſſum eſt &amp; evangelizare &amp; baptizare &amp; Scripturas in Eccleſia ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>planare.</hi> That which he ſaith of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> perſons publiſhing the Goſpel, is ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtified by that which we reade Act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> viii. 4. <hi>Therefore they that were ſca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered abroad, went everywhere preach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the word.</hi> And again, Acts xi. 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115813:54"/> 
               <hi>Now they which were ſcattered abroad upon the perſecution that aroſe about Stephen, travelled as farre as Phoenice and Cyprus and Antiochia, preaching the Word to none but unto the Jews onely.</hi> That which he ſaith of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the Scriptures, that is, <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church,</hi> will be juſtified no leſſe, if it be referred to that variety of gifts ſpecified out of the Apoſtle, moſt an end miraculous and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that time, the uſe whereof was for edification in the aſſemblies. And the reaſon that is to be given for this muſt needs appear very conſiderable; Becauſe that among men choſen out of thoſe that were newly converted to the faith in their elder years, for which they are called PRESEYTERS, and that in reſpect of other kind of abilities tending to other parts of their office, there ſhould be found men fit to ſpeak in publick aſſemblies upon humane parts and indeavours, ſo as
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:115813:55"/> to preſerve the <hi>decorum</hi> and reverence of ſo great a work, is beyond the compaſſe of common diſcretion to imagine; theſe qualities being not often found but in thoſe that are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituated to them from their youth. Do but look on thoſe of our Lords kindred that confeſſed him before Domitian, and therefore were made leaders of Churches, as was related before from Hegeſippus, and think whether men whoſe hands were hardned with the plough, already ſtruck in years, were fit to make Preachers when they were made Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Churches: So farre is it from us to think that in the cradle of the Church no Presbyter was made, but for his abilities in preaching. Let us now look back a little upon the plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form pretended, and ask what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion men have to turn temporary indowments into perpetuall places? or according to perſonall gifts and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115813:55"/> graces to diſtinguiſh oecumenicall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices? (And yet it will not appear that ever Paſtours were diſtinguiſhed from Doctours by the Apoſtle: For he never ſaid that Chriſt hath given <hi>ſome Paſtours, ſome Doctours;</hi> but his words are, Epheſ. iv. 11. that he gave <hi>ſome Pastours and Doctours,</hi> having ſaid afore that <hi>he gave ſome Apostles, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Prophets,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing thoſe, but compriſing theſe.) If Teaching and Preaching muſt make two offices, as then they were two graces, why ſhall not Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting come in for a ſhare, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that there may be an office in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for the purpoſe of it, as well as for Teaching, which it ſtandeth in equipage with, Rom, xii. 7, 8? why ſhould not the word of Wiſdome and the word of Knowledge do the like? for theſe mentioned 1. Cor. xii. 8. are of perpetuall uſe, although Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and ſtrange languages were but
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:115813:56"/> for the time. There is one good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be given and no more: Becauſe perpetuall Miniſteries are one thing, temporary Gifts are another thing: Thoſe we know, by the inſtitution of them in Scripture, by the office of them ſpecified in the Acts and in the Epiſtles, by the practice of them in all ages of the Church; thoſe we know were in time of the Apoſtle, but not inſtituted for Miniſteries, becauſe not continued. The Office of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters we know was both for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Teaching: Both are found in S. Peters exhortation to the Presbyters of his charge, 1. Pet. v. 2. <hi>feeding</hi> the flock, and <hi>overſeeing</hi> it: both in S. Pauls charge to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyters of Epheſus, Acts xx. 28. and afterwards: both in the qualities of Biſhops, (that is, as is acknowledged, of Presbyters) wherein Timothy is inſtructed by the Apoſtle, 1. Tim. iii. 2, 5. both conteined in that very paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:115813:56"/> that is alledged to bring in a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Presbyters, 1. Tim. v. 17. For thoſe Elders that <hi>rule well</hi> are ſuch as <hi>labour in the word and doctrine:</hi> Why might not the Apoſtle then difference Presbyters by the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their functions as well as by the functions themſelves? Why might not ſome Presbyters ſhew more diligence in the moſt eminent point of the office, taking ſpeciall pains in the Word and Doctrine, which ſpeciall pains the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth, and yet others be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worthy of double honour, and good Rulers, as well in reſpect of their diligence in the prime point as of their performance in the reſt? The perſonall gifts of the Holy Ghoſt were then diſtributed on ſeverall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as the Apoſtle ſheweth, that all might be uſefull, and ſuch indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the time of ſpirituall graces, might be imployed to the edification
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:115813:57"/> of aſſemblies as well as the gifts of ruling, to aſſiſt the Presbyters in their office of Government: But he that would take order now, that who could pretend a gift in ruling ſhould be helpers in government, or in the word of Wiſdome and Knowledge, ſhould ſtand up to edifie aſſemblies, might ſoon find more help in govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, more words of Wiſdome and Knowledge, and in time more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying, then himſelf would deſire. Well may we turn the world into confuſion, if we think to do what then was done; but ſhall never find any Miniſteries of place and ſucceſſion in the Church but Presbyters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons (for of the coming-in of Biſhops hath been ſaid) to the parts of whoſe office, conſiſting in Ruling, Teaching, and Miniſtering, all thoſe other gifts of the holy Ghoſt are to be referred as aſſiſtant at that time; and from whoſe office, and the ordinary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:115813:57"/> of God upon it, the effect of them all is to be expected at this time. For let me ask, What is become of thoſe <hi>Doctours,</hi> diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Pastours,</hi> in all ſucceeding ages? Where have thoſe <hi>ruling Elders</hi> hid themſelves, that they were never ſeen ſince the time of the Apoſtles? Is it poſſible that the whole Church ſhould conſpire to ſuppreſſe ſuch an inſtitution of our Lord and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles almoſt as ſoon as it was made? Or is it imaginable, had it not been ſuppreſſed, that all Eccleſiaſticall wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whereof there is ſuch ſtore, ſhould conſpire ſo farre to ſuppreſſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of it, that among them all there is not one witneſſe produced to depoſe for them, unleſſe it be by thoſe that bring the meaning with them which they deſire to find in their writings? Were we alive in Tertullians time, we might go into the aſſemblies of Chriſtians, and ſee
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:115813:58"/> with our eyes what now will not be believed, though it be told us in terms plain enough to them that will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, when he ſaith as afore, <hi>Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent probati quique ſeniores, honorem non pretio ſed teſtimonio adepti.</hi> We might ſee them ſitting in the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room of the Congregation by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves apart from the people: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they are called by him other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles <hi>Ordo</hi> and <hi>Conſeſſus.</hi> And were there occaſion to ſee any of them cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured to the loſſe of his office, we might ſee him for his puniſhment ſit and communicate in the rank of the people. It hath not been my lot yet to meet with any thing in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Writers, or out of them, to bear an appearance of this difference, but onely thoſe words of the commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries under S. Ambroſe his name upon 1. Tim. v. 1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde &amp; Synagoga, &amp; poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea Eccleſia, Seniores habuit, ſine quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conſilio nihil agebatur in Eccleſia.</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:115813:58"/> He ſpeaketh in the time paſt, of that which had been in the Church and was not; and without doubt giveth men of excellent abilities, men of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable merit in the Church, occaſion to miſtake his meaning, as if he had ſpoke of a ſort of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which had been in the Church and now were not: whereas they ſhould have taken the whole clauſe with them, when he ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde &amp; poſtea Eccleſia Seniores habuit, ſine quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conſilio nihil agebatur in Eccleſia;</hi> and then his meaning had been plain, as in truth it is, That the Church once had Presbyters that joyned adviſe with the Biſhop in all Church-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; which my deſire is to prove was ſo from the beginning, and which he complaineth was now otherwiſe. For ſo S. Hierome, about the ſame time, manifeſtly declareth that he thought an alteration in this point was come to paſſe, when he ſaith that at the firſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:115813:59"/> Churches were governed by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon adviſe, but afterwards all was referred to one, hereupon exhorting Biſhops to communicate the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Churches with their Presbyters, as Moſes did his with the Sanedrin of Iſrael. And this further appeareth by that which followeth in the ſaid Commentaries, <hi>Quod quâ negligentiâ obſoleverit, neſcio, niſi fortè Doctorum quorundam deſidiâ, vel po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs ſuperbiâ dum ſoli volunt aliquid videri,</hi> imputing the change to the negligence of <hi>Teachers,</hi> or to their pride: and therefore they are <hi>Teachers</hi> that were called <hi>Elders</hi> afore; and through their negligence, or the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops taking all on themſelves, all came into their hands: which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may be referred to that which by and by ſhall be ſaid, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops afterwards in ſome parts took the office of preaching in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Church, where they lived, in a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:115813:59"/> ſort to their peculiar, not ſuffering the Presbyters to preach in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Which office of preaching ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, as the matter is now, being become the neceſſary charge of Biſhop and Presbyters (tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary graces being ceaſed, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſes divided, Churches built, and means aſſigned) as it is without doubt and alwayes was accounted, in regard of perſonall performance, the moſt excellent work they are able to contribute to the ſervice of God, ſo is it for the uſe of edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as much to be preferred before other their imployment, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying is by the Apoſtle prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before ſpeaking with ſtrange languages: Alwayes provided (ſince we muſt not now preſume upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate inſpirations, but expect Gods ordinary bleſſing upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane indeavours) that men and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities may be ſtored for the work
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:115813:60"/> before the work be cut out for them, ſo as the honour and reverence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be preſerved without offenſe. For as the Apoſtle ſaith, that if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers ſhould come into the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Chriſtians, and heare them nothing but ſpeak languages which moſt underſtood not, they would ſay they were mad: So if the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Profeſſion ſhould heare in our Churches a great deal of tongue, but the meaning of the Scripture not in it, needs muſt this bring an evil opinion upon it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:115813:60"/>
            <head>CHAP. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Offices of Divine ſervice, performed in chief by the Biſhop: after him by the Presbyters. Order of Chriſtian Aſſemblies appointed by Biſhop and Presbyters. Maintenance of the Church and poore diſpoſed of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>VVEll then, this particular of labour in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is out of doubt common to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Presbyters both. It is that which S. Peter moſt aimeth at, when he exhorteth thoſe whom he calleth his <hi>fellow-Elders</hi> to the office of feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the flock: It is that which S. Paul for the moſt part expreſſeth, when he exhorteth the Presbyters of Epheſus to <hi>take heed to the flock which they were to feed,</hi> Acts xx. 28. according to his example, that <hi>ceaſed not to warn every one night and day with tears,</hi> verſe 31.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:115813:61"/> 
               <hi>teaching them both in publick, and from houſe to houſe,</hi> as it is afore, v. 28. And we ſhall find this office of teaching and inſtructing the Church to reſt after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon the Biſhop in chief, and upon the Presbyters in conſequence, whether in private upon particular occaſions, whereof we find much ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of practice in S. Cyprians Epiſtles, or in publick in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Chriſtians. For thus the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter went afterwards, the principall parts and offices of Divine ſervice, that is, the Sermon and the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Euchariſt, were wont to be reſerved to the Biſhop, in honour of his place and the eminence of it, unleſſe he were abſent or it were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of otherwiſe. Which I take to be the reaſon why Juſtine Martyr, in the place alledged afore, related that the Sermon was wont to be made and the Euchariſt celebrated by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which name compriſeth Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:115813:61"/> and Presbyters both as hath been ſaid; becauſe the office belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Biſhop in the firſt place, to the Presbyters in caſe of his abſence, or the like. And you ſhall heare even now Ignatius his argument to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Epheſians not to aſſemble for the Euchariſt, but with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if the prayers of one or two have that force, that Chriſt is in the midſt of them, much more the prayers of the Biſhop and Church;</hi> Therefore it was the Biſhop whoſe prayers the Euchariſt was celebrated with. And in the Life of S. Auguſtine is related, that it was not the cuſtome for Presbyters to preach in the Churches of Africk, (that is, not if the Biſhop were preſent) whereupon the Biſhop Valerius being a Greek, and not ſo fit to ſpeak to the people in Latine, brought that into uſe there which he had ſeen practiced in the Eaſt, and aſſumed S. Auguſtine to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:115813:62"/> him by preaching in his preſence. The Commentarie under S. Ambroſe his name ſo often alledged, having ſaid, upon Epheſ. iv. 11. as we had it afore, that at the firſt all ſorts preached in the Church, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it was otherwiſe ſettled, proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth it with theſe words, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde nunc neque Diaconi in populo praedicant.</hi> And of Baptizing, Tertullian <hi>l. De Baptiſt. c.</hi> 17. <hi>Dandi quidem jus habet ſummus ſacerdos, id eſt, Epiſcopus, dehinc Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri &amp; Diaconi, ſed non ſine autoritate Epiſcopi propter Eccleſiae honorem, quo ſalvo ſalvapax eſt.</hi> To ſhew us, That all ſervices of the Church, even to baptize, belonged in chief to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, in reſpect to his place; that for the ſame reaſon the Presbyters were ſilent in their preſence; and the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons not ſuffered at all to preach at that time. Now as the office com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to Biſhop and Presbyters was and is ſeen in the ſervices of the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:115813:62"/> Church, ſo was it alſo ſeen in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the aſſemblies of the Church for that purpoſe. This we have here to obſerve out of Ignatius his Epiſtles, in conſequence to that which was produced afore out of S. Paul and Clemens concerning the diſorders of the aſſemblies at Corinth; that to correct them, and to prevent the like, the order of the peoples Oblations, of the Presbyters celebrating the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, of the Aſſemblies of the Church for that purpoſe, was regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the appointment of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Presbyters. His words are theſe. <hi>Epiſt. ad Smyrn.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That <hi>without the Biſhop,</hi> neither the people might <hi>bring their offerings,</hi> nor Presbyters <hi>conſecrate the Euchariſt,</hi> nor both <hi>celebrate the feasts of Love</hi> uſed at theſe aſſemblies. And for the purpoſe of this particular it is that he
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:115813:63"/> is ſo earneſt and frequent throughout his Epiſtles in exhorting to be ſubject to the Biſhop and Presbyters. <hi>Epiſt. ad Trall.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He that is within the Altar,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is pure: wherefore he obeyeth the Biſhop and Presbyters: But he that is without, is he that doth any thing without the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Presbyters.</hi> He that is <hi>without the Altar,</hi> in Ignatius his terms, <hi>that doth things without the Biſhop and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyters,</hi> is meant of thoſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that aſſembled, or thoſe of the Presbyters that celebrated the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, without the Biſhop and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyters or their appointment: which was called <hi>erecting Altar againſt Altar</hi> in the Primitive time: For ſo Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius again in the Epiſtle to the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, <hi>Let no man miſtake,</hi> ſaith he; <hi>if a man be not within the Altar, he</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:115813:63"/> 
               <hi>cometh ſhort of the bread of God. For if the prayer of one or two be of ſuch force, that Christ ſtandeth in the middeſt of them, how much more ſhall the prayer wherein the Biſhop and Church agreeth</hi> (that is, at the Euchariſt, which he ſpoke of when he mentioned <hi>the bread of God</hi> afore) <hi>prevail?</hi> And therefore in the end of that Epiſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Obeying the Biſhop and Presbyters without diſtraction of mind, breaking one bread, which is the medicine of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</hi> A plain caſe: The intent of his exhortations is, to perſwade them to aſſemble without ſchiſme, becauſe that to aſſemble and celebrate the Euchariſt beſides the Biſhops ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment was then the due marke of aſchiſmatick. And that the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concurred with him in ordering theſe matters, appeareth by the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience he requireth to both: And ſo
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:115813:64"/> ſtill in Ignatius the Presbyters are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant to the Biſhop in all things. And this is the meaning of that vi<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Canon of the Councel at Gangra, whereof the tenour is, <hi>If any man aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble in private beſide the Church, and will perform Eccleſiaſticall Offices in contempt of the Church, no Presbyter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there with aſſent of the Biſhop, let him be anathema:</hi> Providing herein againſt ſchiſme, as the occaſion of that Councel evidenceth. Wherewith agreeth the xxxii. Canon of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. And in the vii<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and viii<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Canon next following of the ſame Councel there is proviſion againſt bringing or receiving oblations o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then to the Church, beſide the Biſhops mind, or his that is truſted for theſe things, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the poore, under pain of <hi>ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema:</hi> The heavineſſe of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence proceeding upon the mark of ſchiſme which the action forbidden
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:115813:64"/> importeth, though there is in it a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the maintenance of the Church and poore ariſing for that time out of the oblations of Chriſtian people, the diſperſing whereof was then another particular of the office common to Biſhop and Presbyters. For as we reade acts xi. 29. that the benevolence of the brethren of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia was directed to the Elders at Jeruſalem by the hands of Barnabas and Saul, though the ſeven Deacons were made afore to attend upon the poore; ſo are we not to think that their office went ſo high as to diſpoſe of their maintenance, but to execute the diſpoſition of Biſhop and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. For when the Church of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochia mainteined foure thouſand poore, as is read in a paſſage of S. Chryſoſtome, the Church of Rome two thouſand and five hundred in Cornelius his time, as is to be ſeen in his words related by Euſebius,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:115813:65"/> 
               <hi>Eccleſ. hiſt.</hi> vi. 43. it is not reaſon to imagine that all this means was put in the power of the Deacons: Whoſe office S. Hierome well expreſſeth when he calleth them <hi>menſarum ac vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duarum miniſtros,</hi> as thoſe that <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred</hi> not <hi>diſpoſed</hi> of their maintenance. (Though perhaps the advantage of fingring money was it that made them take ſo much upon them in his time, whereof he complaineth) Nay, it is plain this muſt reſt in the power of Biſhop and Presbyters by the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diviſions thereof, wherein each of them had intereſſe, as his maintenance; whereof we find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance in S. Cyprians Epiſtles. In the laſt Canon of the Councel of Antiochia is provided, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſhall not alienate the Church-goods (which though immovable, were given for the ſame purpoſe) without conſent of his Presbyters. And in thoſe which are called the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:115813:65"/> Canons of the Apoſtles (which the world knoweth are not theirs, but yet do expreſſe very ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the Church) <hi>Can.</hi> iii. <hi>&amp;</hi> iv. having ordered what ſorts of firſt-fruits ſhould be ſent to the Church, what home to the Biſhop and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyters, it followeth, <hi>Now it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that they are to be divided by them among the Deacons and Clergy:</hi> to the Deacons, for the maintenance of the poore; to the Clergy, for their own: Where you ſee the intereſſe of the Presbyters in diſpoſing of ſuch oblations.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:115813:66"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the diſcipline of Penance. Thoſe that have the Keyes remit ſinnes by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Penance. The interceſsion of the Church. Particular perſons excommunicated among the Jews. Our Lord prohibiteth their courſe among his Diſciples. Two degrees of Excommunication as well in the Church as in the Synagogue. The Keyes are given to Biſhop and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyters. The intereſſe of the people, and what is required at the hands of the Common-wealth.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THere remaineth now two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the office common to Biſhop and Presbyters, wherein the people alſo claim their intereſſe: the one is the diſcipline of Penance; the other the making of Miniſters: The due courſe whereof aſſigned by our Lord and his Apoſtles will beſt be
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:115813:66"/> diſcovered, laying together firſt what we find of them in Scripture, and then comparing of it with the proceeding of the Primitive time, which we ſhall perceive the right to go along with. The Keyes of the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are given by our Lord to the firſt of his Diſciples, in thoſe words, Matth. xvi. 19. <hi>And I will give thee the keyes of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and whatſoever thou bindeſt on earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou ſhalt looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</hi> If mens minds were not poſſeſſed with prejudice, it would ſoon appear to be the ſame power that is given to all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, John xx. 24. <hi>Whoſeſoever ſinnes ye remit, they are remitted unto them; and whoſeſoever ſinnes ye retein, they are reteined.</hi> But Matt. xviii. 17, 18. to the ſame purpoſe, though more at large, <hi>And if he ſhall neglect to heare them, tell it unto the Church: But if he</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:115813:67"/> 
               <hi>neglect to heare the Church, let him be unto thee as a heathen man and as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican. Verily I ſay unto you, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ye ſhall bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven; and whatſoever ye looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> To this muſt be added the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the Apoſtle, in delivering to Satan the inceſtuous perſon at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. 1. Cor. v. 3, 4, 5. which he alſo did to Hymeneus and Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. 1. Tim. i. 20. Now, in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Primitive Church, thoſe that exerciſed this power, were in part Judges <hi>(Cenſours</hi> you may call them, if you pleaſe) and in part Phyſicians. Both parts compriſed in S. Cyprians words, <hi>Ep.</hi> 51. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi lapſis nec cenſura deeſt quae increpet, nec medicina quae ſanet.</hi> Judges they are in ſhutting Gods houſe upon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, and binding their ſins upon their conſciences. And the effect of this cenſure ſuch, (ſuppoſing the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:115813:67"/> proceeding of it to be due) that as the diſeaſe of ſin is not to be cured with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the medicine of repentance, no more can this knot wherewith ſinnes, notorious of themſelves, or otherwiſe known, are tyed to mens conſciences, be undone without known repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. For ſince the worſt of the ſouls ſickneſſe conſiſteth in not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging her diſeaſe, it pleaſed God to give his Church power and charge to conſtrain offenders to take their Phyſick, which the grief of bodily diſeaſes is able to do alone. Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans they are then, in preſcribing the medicine of Repentance: and in that reſpect alone are truly ſaid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinnes. God himſelf ſaith not to the Soul, <hi>I abſolve thee from thine offenſes,</hi> but upon ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the means, his own gift of repentance, that worketh the cure: ſo farre it is from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his creature to pronounce
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:115813:68"/> forgiveneſſe without knowledge of the effect which the medicine of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance hath wrought. But if we ſay true when a Phyſician is ſaid to cure a mans diſeaſe, though all the world know he doth no more but preſcribe the medicine, or at the moſt ſee it applyed; with as good right is it to be ſaid that mens ſinnes are cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them that preſcribe the courſe by which they are cured. Onely, whereas he that is cured of a bodily diſeaſe is able to tell himſelf when he is well; he that is once ſenſible of the maladies of his ſoul, is not eaſily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied when the cure is done: It hath therefore pleaſed the goodneſſe of God to provide an office and charge in his Church to aſſure men of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſinnes upon due know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of repentance, by taking away that knot wherewith they remained tied upon their conſciences. Firmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea Cappadociae</hi>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:115813:68"/> in his Epiſtle to S. Cyprian, the lxxv<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in number of his Epiſtles, thus writeth, <hi>Lapſis quoque fratribus per poenitentiam medela quaeratur. Non quaſi à nobis remiſsionem peccatorum conſequantur, ſed ut per nos ad intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam delictorum ſuorum convertan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; Domino pleniùs ſatisfacere co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur.</hi> To this purpoſe was the time and order and faſhion of Penance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated in the ancient Church, that the diſeaſes of the ſoul might receive every one their competent cure: and therefore it is plain that among them it was a favour to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Penance, in oppoſition to Novatianus, <hi>Qui nemini dandam poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam putavit,</hi> ſaith Saint Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, <hi>De Poenit.</hi> 2. 1. exhorting men to repentance indeed, but leaving them for pardon to God who had power to give it, as his Diſciple So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates writeth <hi>Eccleſ. hiſt.</hi> iv. 13. That is, not imploying the power of the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:115813:69"/> keyes, and the benefit of it, to the cure of their offenſes. Whereupon S. Ambroſe you ſee calleth it <hi>dare poenitentiam,</hi> as on the offenders ſide it was then called <hi>petere poenitentiam,</hi> demanding and granting of Penance. For this cauſe it was that this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine of repentance was wont to be joyned with the prayers of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, but in the chief place, of the Biſhop and Presbyters; which, if repentance be Phyſick, is correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to that which is given to make Phyſick work: And this is called in Tertullian, <hi>Presbyteris advolvi, Caris Dei adgeniculari, Omnibus fratribus le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationes deprecationis ſuae injungere;</hi> and in S. Auguſtine, <hi>Gemitus columbae,</hi> the Mourning of the turtle, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their releaſe at Gods hands. And to this purpoſe was the Impoſition of hands ſo often repeated in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, becauſe as S. Auguſtine ſaith of it, in confirmation (wherein he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:115813:69"/> Tertullian: the one in theſe words, <hi>Quid enim eſt impoſitio manuum niſi oratio ſuper hominem?</hi> the other afore him in theſe, <hi>Dehinc manus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur per benedictionem advocans &amp; invitans Spiritum Sanctum,</hi> That it is but a Ceremony of benediction, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the overſhadowing of the Holy Ghoſt which it repreſenteth: So was it in Penance nothing elſe but a form of benediction, interceding for their reconcilement. This may very well be thought to be the intent of the words of our Lord, in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel alledged, Matth. xviii. 19. For having delivered to the Church the power of binding and looſing in the words recited, it followeth ſtraight, <hi>Again, I ſay unto you, that if two of you ſhall agree on earth as touching any thing that they ſhall ask, it ſhall be done for them of my Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: for where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in my Name, there am</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:115813:70"/> 
               <hi>I in the midſt of them.</hi> For as in the words next going afore, he ſheweth how mens ſins are bound and looſed, to wit by the power which he giveth his Church to that purpoſe, ſo he may well ſeem in the next words to point at the courſe by which this power may become effectuall to the looſing of ſinnes, to wit the interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Congregation of Gods people. At leaſt, thus much hath been obſerved by men of excellent learning, that lamenting is a work ſpecified by the Apoſtle himſelf in the buſineſſe of reducing offenders by Penance, 1. Cor. v. 2. <hi>Ye have not lamented to put away ſuch a tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from you.</hi> And again, 2. Cor. xii. 20. <hi>I fear that when I come unto you, I ſhall not find you ſuch as I deſire, and ſhall bewail many which have ſinned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and have not repented of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, and fornication, and laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe that they have committed:</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:115813:70"/> meaning that he ſhould put them to Penance, by conſequence. This ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the intereſſe of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the work of Diſcipline to be conſiderable, but intituleth it not to the keyes of Gods houſe. For to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our Lords meaning aright, let us take notice that there was among the Jews much uſe of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by particular perſons; (as is to be ſeen in their writings: <hi>Maimoni</hi> in <hi>Talmud Torah,</hi> c. 7. <hi>Arba Turim,</hi> or <hi>Shulchan Aruch,</hi> in <hi>Tore Deah, Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coth Niddui <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cherem)</hi> and that many times upon cauſes of their particular intereſſe: For example, a Rabbi or Rabbies Mate was able to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate for his credit, when he found himſelf ſlighted. True it is, they count it commendable in a Rabbi to paſſe over all diſreſpect to himſelf in private, but he that ſhall do it in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, they bind him to remember it, and watch his party like a Serpent,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:115813:71"/> till he ſeek favour and reconcilement; Maimoni, <hi>n. ult.</hi> And true it is that in ſome caſes they void excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is grounded upon particular intereſſe, and not for the honour of God, <hi>Jore Deah out of the Hieruſalem Talmud and R. Joſeph Karo upon it, f.</hi> 364. And generally, he that excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth without cauſe, is to be excommunicated himſelf; (it is the laſt of twenty foure cauſes for which they excommunicate) but what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders might come upon ſuch pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, is eaſie to imagine. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is great cauſe to think, that our Lords words whereof we ſpeak are aimed on purpoſe to abrogate this courſe among his followers, though covertly to avoyd offenſe. For two things he preſcribeth in oppoſition to it; firſt to aim at a brothers reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and nothing elſe in all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, Matt. xviii. 15. <hi>If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall treſpaſſe againſt thee, go and</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:115813:71"/> 
               <hi>tell him his fault between thee and him alone: If he ſhall heare thee, thou hast gained thy brother.</hi> The ſecond is, that they ſhall proceed no further then conteſtation in private; the reſt he preſcribeth to be referred in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to the Church: So it followeth, <hi>But if he will not heare thee, then take with thee one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three witneſſes every word may be establiſhed. And if he ſhall neglect to heare them, tell it unto the Church.</hi> Now this word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Church,</hi> as alſo. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is firſt uſed in the Greek of the old Teſtament, to ſignifie the Congregation of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael. The Jews that have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſince the Prophets have eſpouſed and appropriated this later word the <hi>Synagogue</hi> to ſignifie ſometimes the whole body of that Nation, or rather of that Faith (as among the Fathers <hi>the Synagogue</hi> ſtandeth for the Jews, in oppoſition to the Church of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians)
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:115813:72"/> ſometimes particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of it, and by conſequence the place of their aſſemblies, as in the Goſpel, <hi>He loveth our nation, and hath built us a Synagogue.</hi> And juſt ſo in all reſpects is the word ECCLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIA, <hi>the Church,</hi> uſed in relation to Chriſtians, our Lord in the Goſpel having begun to appropriate it to the Congregation which he now began to inſtitute, Matt. xvi. 18. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this rock will I build my Church:</hi> and in the text in hand, Matt. xviii. 17. <hi>Tell it to the Church.</hi> So that it muſt not be denied, it is not uſuall for the <hi>Church,</hi> which ſignifieth the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of people, to ſignifie the chief part of it. But it is as certain on the other ſide, that looking backward to the Synagogue upon which our Lord reflecteth, as was ſaid, ſuch cenſures as theſe are whereof our Lord ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, proceeding from the public (private ones being excluded as hath
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:115813:72"/> been ſaid) iſſued all from the Courts of Juſtice mentioned afore, without reſpect to the Congregation of the people. As thus: There were among them two degrees of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and no more, the leſſe called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>Separation,</hi> the greater <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Anathema,</hi> and the effect of them, to cut a man off, more or leſſe, from the Congregation of the people, (as is to be ſeen in the late moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed work, <hi>De Jure Nat. &amp; Gent. ſec. diſc. Ebr.</hi> iiii. 9.) The ordinary ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Separation, which is that we ſpake of afore, was for thirtie dayes, unleſſe the Court thought fit to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge or inlarge the term: for that time no man muſt come within foure cubits of him that ſtood excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate beſides thoſe of his houſe; he muſt not be reckoned among three which is the number required at Bleſſing of meat; he muſt not be reckoned among tenne, which is the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:115813:73"/> number required to make a Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue: under that they go not to prayers in the Synagogue. And how it is in the power of the Court to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate this, is to be ſeen in Shulchan Aruch, as afore <hi>Num.</hi> x. At thirty dayes end they iterated the ſentence, and ſtayed thirty dayes more: If then he ſtood out, it was in their power to excommunicate him with curſes, which is that which is called <hi>Anathema.</hi> With theſe the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Chriſtian Church keep ſome correſpondence, according to Scripture. For when our Lord ſaith, <hi>If he heare not the Church, let him be unto thee as a Heathen man and as a Publicane,</hi> he intimateth withall a courſe the Church had to take for his correction and amendment that ſhould give car to it. Which as it might perhaps end in a verball admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the Church and reall amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the party, yet thoſe that were
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:115813:73"/> under the diſcipline of Penance, we know, were in a ſort excommunicate, becauſe they were not admitted to the Communion of the Euchariſt, beſides that (as thoſe which were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated among the Jews) they put upon them the ſtate and faſhion and habit of mourners: And I ſhewed afore what we find in Scripture to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue this courſe directed by our Lord, and practiced by the Apoſtle. But here was a difference, that in that ſtate we find not that a man was cut off from the converſation of Chriſtians, thoſe w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> were admitted to Penance, being alwaies accounted in the way of ſalvation, ſuppoſing the performance of their injoyned Penance. That was the effect of that grievous cenſure whereof our Lord ſpeaketh, <hi>Let him be unto thee as a Heathen man and as a Publicane.</hi> Not becauſe he meaneth to forbid Chriſtians to converſe with Heathen men and Publicanes, who
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:115813:74"/> being to be converted from among them, muſt needs be compaſſed with them on every ſide: And therefore that caſe the Apoſtle hath reſolved, 1. Cor. v. 9, 10. where he informeth them that whereas he had <hi>written to them not to converſe with fornicatours,</hi> his meaning was not to forbid them to converſe with <hi>the fornicatours of this world,</hi> that is Gentiles, or with <hi>the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, or extortioners,</hi> or with <hi>idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: for then muſt ye go out of the world;</hi> and as it followeth verſ. 12. <hi>For what have I to do to judge thoſe that are without? do not ye judge thoſe that are within?</hi> But our Lords meaning is, that Chriſtians ſhould ſhew that reſpect to a brother that ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary to the Church, as the Jews did then to Gentiles and Publicanes, which the Apoſtle ſecondeth there, verſ. 11. <hi>Now I write to you not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, if any man that is called a brother be a fornicatour, or covetous, or an ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later,</hi>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:115813:74"/> 
               <hi>or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner, with ſuch a one no not to eat:</hi> which is to avoid them, as the Jews did him that ſtood ſeparate. And the ſentence whereupon this is to be practiced is intimated in the next verſe, <hi>For what have I to do to judge thoſe that are without? Do not ye judge thoſe that are within?</hi> And this cenſure it ſeemeth the Apoſtle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth when he writeth to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus iii. 11. <hi>A man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admonition, reject.</hi> For his meaning is not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct Titus alone what he in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould do, but in the perſon of Titus to inſtruct all the Church to reject and avoid refractary Hereticks: and therefore in the conſequence of avoyding them, it ſeemeth he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mateth the cenſure whereupon they are to be avoyded. The ſame cenſure againſt the inceſtuous perſon at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth he intimateth by the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:115813:75"/> when he ſaith, 1. Cor. v. 13. <hi>Therefore put away from you that wicked perſon,</hi> which he calleth <hi>giving over to Satan</hi> in the ſame caſe verſ. 5. afore, and in the caſe of Hymeneus and Alexander, 1. Tim. i. 20. and which he ſignifieth 1. Cor. xvi. 22. <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus, let him be anathema Maranatha:</hi> where <hi>ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> is the term that cometh from the Synagogue, and ſo doth the other as ſome men think. So that this cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure cutteth men off from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of Chriſtians, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit the priviledges to which they pretend, and ſo delivers them to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan by conſequence; as thoſe that lodged without the camp of Iſrael, were in danger to be lickt up by the Amalekite. Which courſe neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, as it was preſervative in regard of ſome members, that they might not be tainted, as the Apoſtle ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when he ſaith 1. Cor. v. 6. <hi>Know</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:115813:75"/> 
               <hi>ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump?</hi> So was it medicinall in reſpect of the ſick, ſhame and grief being a good way to the cure: which the Apoſtle ſeemeth to reſpect when he directeth, 1. Cor. v. 6. <hi>to deliver him to Satan for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit might be ſafe in the day of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> and 1. Tim. i. 20. <hi>whom I have delivered to Satan, that they may learn not to blaſpheme.</hi> This is the correſpondence between the proceeding of the Church and Synagogue. And therefore, as look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backward to the Synagogue whereupon our Lord reflecteth when he ſaith, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae,</hi> we ſee to whom they had recourſe, ſo ſhall we ſee, looking forwards upon the Church, which our Lord pointeth towards in the ſame words, to whom he direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his followers to have recourſe. The Keyes of Gods houſe are given in the Goſpel to S. Peter, with the effect of <hi>binding</hi> and <hi>looſing,</hi> and the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:115813:76"/> ſame power to all the Apoſtles, in equivalent terms of <hi>reteining</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting</hi> ſinnes: For if there were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, it were an inconvenience that in the third place the power of <hi>bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>looſing</hi> ſhould be given to the Church, which is pretended given to S. Peter for a priviledge beyond the Apoſtles. Well then might S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian argue, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 27. that becauſe our Lord promiſed to S. Peter the keyes of his Church, therefore the acts of government of it were to paſſe through the Biſhops hands, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him Apoſtates could not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled. And it is the ſame which S. Auguſtine affirmeth ſo oft as he teacheth (which many times he doth) that S. Peter in receiving the Keyes repreſented the Church, as <hi>Ep.</hi> 79. <hi>Si hoc in Eccleſiâ fit</hi> (he ſpeaketh of binding and looſing) <hi>Petrus quando claves accepit Eccleſiam ſanctam ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavit.</hi> For what was promiſed to S.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:115813:76"/> Peter was given the reſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but was to reſt in the Church, to which it is alſo given in the ſame terms; as S. Cyprian is willing to acknowledge, ſo oft as he calleth the Presbyters his Colleagues, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth to do nothing without their adviſe. So that it is not poſſible to give a more impartiall meaning to the words of our Lord in the Goſpel then the practice of thoſe times hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, when that power was exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in common by the Biſhop and his Presbyters. This it is Tertullian hath ſhewed us, <hi>Apolog. c.</hi> 39. alledged afore, where having commended the gravitie and integritie of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call cenſures, to ſhew by whom they were done, he addeth as afore, <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident probati quique ſeniores, honorem non pretio ſed teſtimonio adepti.</hi> And S. Auguſtines words are plain, which we had afore, <hi>Veniat peccator ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tistites per quos ipſi in Eccleſia claves</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:115813:77"/> 
               <hi>miniſtrantur, &amp; à praepoſitis ſacrorum accipiat ſatisfactionis ſuae modum.</hi> And in S. Cyprian there is ſo much men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of reconcilement by impoſition of hands of the Biſhop and Clergy, that I will ſay no more of it, becauſe this point of all the reſt hath continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a chief imployment of Presbyters in the corrupt and pernicious opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and cuſtomes of the Church of Rome. Let not any man think now that the Apoſtle communicateth this power with the Congregation of the Church of Corinth, when he writeth to them, 1. Cor. v. 4, 5. <hi>being aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with his Spirit, to deliver the ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous perſon to Satan.</hi> For it is plain, that the ſentence is given by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, verſ. 3. where he writeth, <hi>For I verily, as abſent in body but preſent in ſpirit, have judged already, as though I were preſent, concerning him that hath ſo done this deed.</hi> And to cauſe this proceeding to be the better digeſted,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:115813:77"/> he hath vouched his power in the end of the chapter afore, verſe 18. <hi>Now ſome are puffed up, as though I would not come unto you: but I will come unto you ſhortly, if the Lord will, and will know, not the ſpeech of them that are puffed up, but the power. What will you? ſhall I come unto you with a rod, or with the ſpirit of meekneſſe?</hi> Which power otherwhiles he ſetteth before them, in caſe of their diſobedience. And therefore it muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that he writeth to them to ſee his ſentence publiſhed, ratified and executed, which the Presbyters there had either neglected to do, as was touched afore, or perhaps were not able to bring the people under the diſcipline of Chriſts Kingdome; which muſt needs oblige the Apoſtle to interpoſe. And therefore the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian gloſſe of <hi>Diodati,</hi> which maketh the Apoſtle in this place ſpeak of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the Paſtours and Guides of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:115813:78"/> the Church, as in Matth. xviii. 17. though in effect true, (becauſe for certain, what is to be acted by the Congregation, therein the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are to do their part, by the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle) yet muſt leave us room to think, that the words are to be underſtood of the publick aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Church there for Divine ſervice, ſeeing we find in Tertullian the place afore quoted, that theſe cenſures were exerciſed at and in the aſſemblies of the Chriſtian people: <hi>Ibidem etiam exhortationes, caſtigatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; cenſur a divina,</hi> ſaith he, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Aſſemblies. And S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian in the great caſe of thoſe that fell away in perſecution, writeth to the Presbyters that he doth not think to do any thing in it, without their counſel, &amp; the conſent of the people. And this without doubt is the reaſon why the Apoſtle writeth in theſe terms 1. Cor. v. 12. <hi>For what have</hi>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:115813:78"/> 
               <hi>I to do to judge thoſe that are without? do not ye judge thoſe that are within?</hi> ſpeaking to the Church in generall, (though the ſentence paſſed, as hath been ſaid by Biſhop and Presbyters) becauſe matters were cenſured in the Congregation, and executed by the people: And thus the practice of that time giveth a reaſon without ſtraining why our Lord ſeemeth to refer theſe matters to the Congregation, when he ſaith, <hi>Tell it to the Church,</hi> becauſe they paſſed at their aſſemblies, though under cenſure of Biſhop and Presbyters. And great reaſon there is why this regard ſhould be had by the Apoſtle, and by the Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, to the people, becauſe the Church, being a mere ſpirituall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and not indued with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſtrength, ſo much as to execute thoſe ſentences which the power of the keyes given by Chriſt obligeth it to inflict, alwayes ſetting aſide that
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:115813:79"/> power of working miracles, which was in the Apoſtle, upon which ſome think he reflecteth in ſome paſſages of thoſe Epiſtles) requiſite it was then, the Congregation ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of the courſe of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings which muſt come into exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and effect by their voluntary ſubmiſſion to the will of God and the office of his Miniſters: And as the matter is now, that things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proceed not upon mens private conſciences and judgements in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, but upon generall rules of common right, requiſite it is that the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth have ſatisfaction of thoſe laws according to which the Church now muſt proceed in their cenſures, it being acknowledged that they cannot proceed with effect but by virtue of thoſe laws that are put in force by the ſecular arm: But as it is now no longer time to leave matters to the Conſcience of mens
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:115813:79"/> places which may be regulated by laws, which experience maketh commendable; ſo is it no longer time to expect at the peoples hands volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſubmiſſion to the diſcipline of the Church, further then it is inabled by laws of the kingdome to exerciſe it. And therefore it is much to be wiſhed that the laws by which the Miniſters of the Church are inabled, directed, conſtrained to exerciſe this prime part of their office, may prove ſo ſufficient, and that the power of the keyes given it by our Lord in the Goſpel may be ſo ſtrengthened by the ſecular arm, and rules put in force by it, that it may be able to reduce all hainous and notorious offenſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſcipline of Penance, and to cut them off from the Church that refuſe it. Is it to be believed, that our Lords intent was, in ſettling ſuch a power as this is; that it ſhould take hold of ſinnes of incontinence or the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:115813:80"/> like, letting all others, of as deep a ſtain, and as well known, eſcape un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſured? Or could any man deviſe a more puiſſant means to diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance malefactours in a Chriſtian Common-wealth, then that which our Lord hath appointed, by making them know, that when they have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the laws of the kingdome, with loſſe of goods or fame, or have eſcaped with life by the gentleneſſe of them, the fact being proved, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe they can not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the people of God, till the Church be ſatisfied of their correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and amendment? Nay, ſhall we imagine that the inſtitution of our Lord Chriſt is ſatisfied and in force in a Chriſtian Common-wealth, ſo long as the caſe of particular offenſes, upon occaſion whereof it is ſettled by him in the Goſpel, is ſcarce under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood among us, becauſe it is ſo farre from common practice by the law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:115813:80"/> of the kingdome? whereas it might eaſily appear what an excellent and charitable courſe our Saviour hath chalked out to us, if a good Chriſtian heart, deſirous rather of his brothers amendment then of his own ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and able to make an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſuch an offenſe, as our Lord intended, by witneſſes, the Church, inabled by rules of law, eſtabliſhed by the ſecular arm, ſhould call the perſon offending to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of wrong on his ſide, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him off in caſe he refuſed amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus much for certain, if the zeal of well-affected Chriſtians to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſtate of this Church did not miſtake the true mark, the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of Penance, muſt needs be thought one of the firſt points to be reformed in it. And then the reſt of that ſatisfaction which the people can demand of the Church, will conſiſt in not releaſing the correction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:115813:81"/> untill there be reaſonable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the effect wrought by it. For if in S. Cyprians diſcipline, the people reſted ſo unſatisfied of ſome whom his gentleneſſe had reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that they were hardly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to admitte them to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, as he writeth <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55. juſt cauſe have good Chriſtians to be ſcandalized, when they ſee them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to communicate of whoſe offenſes they are ſure, but have no cauſe to be ſure of their amendment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:115813:81"/>
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Ordinations what is remembred in Scripture. The courſe held in the Primitive Church. The Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and constitution of Biſhops upon what grounds. Presbyters had their part in Ordinations:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>was not Election by holding up hands. Ordination of Deacons for common buſineſſe of Churches. The intereſſe of the people is ſatisfied in the courſe now practiced. What the Primitive form requireth in the Conſtitution of Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>AS for the conſtituting and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miniſters, which is behind of my promiſe, theſe are the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars remembred concerning it in Scripture, for the moſt part touched upon occaſion heretofore, Acts xiii. 3. <hi>And when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent</hi>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:115813:82"/> 
               <hi>them away,</hi> Acts xiv. 23. Paul and Barnabas, <hi>when they had ordained them Elders in every Church, and had prayed with faſting, they commended them to the Lord, on whom they believed.</hi> and 1. Tim. iv. 14. <hi>Neglect not the gift that was given thee by prophecy, with the impoſition of hands of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbytery;</hi> which is 2. Tim. i. 6. <hi>by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of my hands.</hi> And the charge of the Apoſtle unto him, 1. Tim. v. 22. <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other mens ſins.</hi> And the whole inſtructions of the Apoſtle to Timothy and Titus, by whom he had appointed them to be ordained. To which muſt be added the choice of Matthias, and the ſeven Deacons, where is ſaid, <hi>that they,</hi> the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, <hi>put up two,</hi> Acts i. 23. <hi>and the twelve ſaid unto them,</hi> Acts vi. 3. <hi>look ye out among you ſeven men of honeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> and verſe 5. <hi>And they choſe Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and the reſt, and verſe 6. <hi>They ſet</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:115813:82"/> 
               <hi>them before the Apoſtles, and when they had prayed they layed hands on them.</hi> Which are alledged by S. Cyprian for the intereſſe of the people in this buſineſſe. Wherein, we ſhall diſcern the courſe of proceeding in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, by that which is read in an Heathen, (who being an enemy to all, can not be thought partiall to any rank of Chriſtians) it is in the life of Alexander Severus, where you have related, how that excellent young Prince, being to promote to the government of Provinces, or the like charges, was wont to ſet up the perſons names, inviting the people to come in againſt any of them upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny crime, whereof they could make evidence, upon pain of life if any failed in it. And then it follows, <hi>Dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bát<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> grave eſſe, cùm id Chriſtiani &amp; Judaei facerent, in praedicandis Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, qui ſunt ordinandi, non fieri in Provinciarum rectoribus, quibus &amp;</hi>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:115813:83"/> 
               <hi>fortunae hominum committerentur &amp; capita.</hi> Theſe words, <hi>in praedicandis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotibus qui ſunt ordinandi,</hi> the learned Caſaubon underſtandeth to be meant of that publication of mens merits and qualities, which muſt needs fall out in diſcuſſing the competence of perſons put up to the approbation of the people to be ordained in any rank of Miniſters in the Aſſemblies of Chriſtians according to the cuſtome then in practice: which cuſtome S. Cyprian commendeth upon the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Eleazar, made and inveſted high Prieſt by Moſes, in ſight of the people, whoſe intereſſe he ſpecifieth when he ſaith, <hi>Ordinationes Sacerdota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſub populi aſsistentis conſcientia fieri, ut plebe praeſente, vel detegantur malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum crimina, vel merit abonorum praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centur, ut ſit ordinatio juſta &amp; legitima, quae omnium ſuffragio &amp; judicio fuerit comprobata.</hi> But before mens deſerts and qualities could be ſcanned, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:115813:83"/> that their perſons ſhould be nominated in the firſt place, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication whereof is called in the ſixth canon of the Chalced on Councel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. where it is provided, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That no man be ordained Presbyter or Deacon, or in any rank of the Church at large, unleſſe he be publiſhed to be ordained in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church of a City or village.</hi> That which is called here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Praedicatio</hi> in Latine, meaning the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of perſons names that were put up to be ordained, ſeems to come nearer that which the Hiſtorian mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when he ſaith <hi>in praedicandis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotibus,</hi> becauſe hereupon follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the examination of their compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which S. Cyprian declareth to be the intereſſe of the people. For if
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:115813:84"/> we conceive that all men indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had the right to nominate, we muſt think a great deal of unſufferable confuſion muſt needs follow at ſuch aſſemblies. And the ſame S. Cyprian when he writeth to his Clergy, Ep. 24. concerning the ordination of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus and Optatus in theſe words, <hi>Quos jampridem communi conſilio Clero proximos feceramus,</hi> excuſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to them that he had ordained them alone, upon this, that they had before promoted them to be next the Clergy by common adviſe, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſheweth that the courſe was to adviſe with the Presbyters and reſt of the Clergy about the perſons to be propounded to the people. We need then no more to ſhew us the courſe of that time. There was firſt nomination of the perſon to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, upon their knowledge and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the perſons, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; there followed impoſition of
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:115813:84"/> hands, wherein conſiſted the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the work, from whence the whole was called in Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>ordinatio</hi> in Latine, compriſeth the whole work whereby they are promoted. In the Ordination of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops there muſt needs be ſomething particular. By the praecedent which S. Hierome hath recorded us, in the Church of Alexandria, where he ſaid afore, that the Presbyters were wont to chuſe a Biſhop out of their own rank, it is plain, their ſtroak was the greateſt in nominating the perſon, to be approved by the people, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the Biſhops. And the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries under Saint Ambroſe his name upon Epheſ. iv. 11. tell us, that at the firſt, the next of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in rank was wont to be aſſumed, (and ſo might it well be practiced in ſome places) untill it was tried that divers times they fell out to be unfit for the place. Then, ſaith he, <hi>immutata</hi>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:115813:85"/> 
               <hi>eſt ratio proſpiciente conſilio, ut non or do ſed meritum crearet Epiſcopum multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Sacerdotum judicio conſtitutum, nè indignus temer è uſurparet, &amp; eſſet mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſcandalum, The courſe was changed upon adviſe which provided, that a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſhould not be made by rank, but by merit, to be eſteemed by the judgement multorum Sacerdotum,</hi> ſignifying by this term as well the Presbyters of the own Church, by whom he was deſired, as the Biſhops of other Churches, by whom he was ordained. For becauſe, according to that which we conceived afore, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning Biſhops were propagated through all Churches, by no other means but by the aſſiſtance of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Churches, that had Biſhops a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hereupon it proceeded to be a cuſtome in the Church, that a Biſhop was not made without approbation and conſent of the neighbour Biſhops, from whom he was to recieve impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:115813:85"/> of hands, and with whom he was to preſerve the unity of the Church, which at that time was actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by no means, but by the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence of Biſhops in the name of their Churches. This is the ground of the cuſtome, that under three Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, it was not uſuall to ordain one. Novatianus was ordained by no leſſe at Rome, in the way of Schiſme, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Cornelius who was ordained by ſixteen, as we reade in S. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. But when the proceeding of this buſineſſe came to be regulated by the Canons of Nice and Antiochia, the Church by that time being incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in the ſtate of the Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, then was it thought fit that a Biſhop ſhould be made by all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of the Province, the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litane, that is, the Biſhop of the head City, in chief, without whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be done, ſo that if ſome few agreed not, the buſineſſe nevertheleſſe
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:115813:86"/> to proceed, and be executed by three at the leaſt. The intent was indeed, ſo farre as opportunity ſhould ſerve, that theſe Acts ſhould be done at the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Synods of Biſhops, to be held twice a year by the fifth Canon of Nice, as may be obſerved among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in that which Saint Auguſtine mentioneth <hi>contra Creſc.</hi> iii. 26. <hi>de veſtris majoribus exſtat ſecundi Tigiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani concilium, cum pauciſsimis quidem factum, apud Cirtam, poſt perſecutionem codicum tradendorum, ut ibi in locum defuncti ordinaretur Epiſcopus.</hi> If no ſuch fell out it was provided, that three might do it, the reſt conſenting under their hands, Can. 19. <hi>Conc. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</hi> Thus, without conſent of the Biſhops all proceedings of Clergy and people were quite diſabled and becalmed, if any faction, any ſiniſter practice appeared in them, and all this upon the charge of the Apoſtle to Timothy, <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no</hi>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:115813:86"/> 
               <hi>man, neither be partaker of other mens ſinnes.</hi> And by virtue of their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, a Biſhop was eſtabliſhed and inveſted, ſo that a Biſhop with Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction before Ordination, was an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate not yet come into the world, ſo long as the primitive cuſtome and rule of the Church was in force, which it ſeemeth ſucceeding cuſtome hath brought to paſſe ſince. Now of all parts of the office common to Biſhop and Presbyters, this of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is that, which the Biſhop firſt began to exerciſe alone, ſo that with S. Chryſoſtome, and S. Hierome, it is taken in a manner for granted, that it was to be done by him alone. The one Hom. 11. in 1. <hi>ad Tim.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Onely in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination the Biſhops go beyond the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, that is it alone which they ſeem to have more than theſe.</hi> The other <hi>Ep. ad Euagr. Quid enim facit Epiſcopus</hi>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:115813:87"/> 
               <hi>except â ordinatione, quod Presbyter non facit?</hi> excepting Ordination, which a Biſhop doth, a Presbyter as he grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth doth not. In which nevertheleſſe (ſetting aſide the ſtroke the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had in making their Biſhops) if we take not our marks amiſſe, we ſhall find argument enough, at leaſt at the beginning, for the concurrence of Presbyters with him in making of Presbyters, and other inferiour Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. In the firſt place, thoſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall paſſages of the Fathers, wherein is witneſſed that the Presbytery was a Bench, aſſiſtant to the Biſhop, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out advice whereof nothing of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was done, muſt needs be drawn into conſequence to argue that it had effect in a particular of this weight. Then the Ordination of Timothy by impoſition of hands of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will prove no leſſe within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the Scripture. Indeed it is well known that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:115813:87"/> in Eccleſiaſticall writers ſignifieth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times the office and rank of Presbyters, which ſignification di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers here embrace, expounding im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands of the Presbytery to mean that by which the rank of Presbyter was conferred. But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles words running as they do, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige a man to ask when he is come as farre as <hi>the impoſition of the hands,</hi> of whom or whoſe hands they were he ſpeaketh of, which the next words ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie; had it been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſenſe might better have been diverted, but running as it doth with the article, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with impoſition of</hi> THE <hi>hands,</hi> it remaineth, that it be ſpecified in the next words, whoſe hands were impoſed, as in the other place, 2. Tim. i. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of my hands.</hi> Thus this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Goſpel, Luke xxii. 66.
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:115813:88"/> And in Ignatius his Epiſtles, ſignifieth the Colledge of Presbyters, which hath the nature and reſpect of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Law, and therefore is read in the ſingular for the whole Bench, and being aſſembled and ſet, is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in both places, and in Cornelius of Rome his Epiſtle to S. Cyprian, where he ſaith, <hi>placuit contrahere Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterium.</hi> But to put the ſignification of the word out of doubt by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the ſenſe, call to mind the Propheſies that went before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Timothy, and compare his caſe with the Apoſtles, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies that went before of him in like caſe, and the impoſition of hands which thereupon both recieved, and ſure it will prove an unreproveable ground, to conclude that what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Apoſtle, is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Diſciple, that theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies coming from the Miniſters of the Church concerning the purpoſe
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:115813:88"/> to which God hath ordained them in his ſervice, occaſioned that which they did about both in giving them impoſition of hands, and that as S. Paul received impoſition of hands from the Presbyters of Antiochia, ſo did Timothy from S. Paul and the Presbyters of that Church which he ſpeaks of but names not. Neither are the arguments of this intereſſe quite worn out of the practice of the Church, either in the point of nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating the perſons, or that of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing hands. For when S. Cyprian expreſſeth himſelf ſo oft in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that it was not his purpoſe to do any thing without advice of his Presbyters and conſent of his people, it is not his meaning that the Clergy ſhould bear no other part in this work then did the multitude, but as they were diſtinct bodies, ſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own words to expect ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice from them, as concerning the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:115813:89"/> perſons to be promoted, but conſent from the people if there were no fault to be found of moment with the perſons deſigned. And in theſe terms the matter ſtands in the 22. Canon of of that which is called the fourth councel of Carthage, where is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Epiſcopus ſine conſilio Clerico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuorum Clericos non ordinet, it à ut civium aſſenſum, &amp; teſtimonium, &amp; conniventiam quaerat.</hi> And as for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands, we have in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle aforeſaid of Firmilianus Biſhop of Caeſarea Cappadocia (if not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the whole act of Ordination) <hi>Omnis poteſtas &amp; gratia in Eccleſia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituta eſt, in qua praeſident majores natu qui &amp; baptizandi &amp; manum imponendi &amp; ordinandi habent poteſtatem.</hi> And in Ignatius his Epiſtle to Hero (whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever writ it, it is ancient enough to ſpeak to our purpoſe) ſpeaking to his Deacon of his Presbyters, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:115813:89"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>They bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, they celebrate the Euchariſt, they impoſe hands in Penance, they ordain, thou miniſtreſt unto them as holy Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen at Jeruſalem to James and the Presbyters.</hi> And where it is provided Conc. Carthag. 4. c. 3. that the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters when the Biſhop giveth impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands ſhall likewiſe impoſe their hands by his, it behoveth us in their caſe alſo to call to mind that this is and was and ought to be, in ſigne of their conſent to what is done, the Apoſtle having ſaid to Timothy, <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other mens ſinnes.</hi> But the intereſſe of the people is inhanſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all meaſure or rule of primitive practice. It will not ſerve the turn that the people had then ſatisfaction of the perſons and their competence to the Miniſteries to which they were ordained, unleſſe we will believe that
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:115813:90"/> when it is ſaid, Acts iv. 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that they were made by moſt voices of the people, ſignified by holding up their hands (as we find in Demoſthenes and others that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to have been in Greekiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalties) Saul and Barnabas doing nothing but moderating the choice, that is in effect telling the voices. And to this purpoſe is alledged that of the Apoſtle, 2. Cor. viii. 19. <hi>And not that onely, but who was alſo choſen of the Churches to travel with us with this grace that is adminiſtred by us:</hi> where in the Greek, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying Election, as they would have it, and not Ordination, ſeeing the office of carrying almes requireth no impoſition of hands. To which let me adde, if they refuſe not that help, the words of Ignatius much in the ſame kind, for in his Epiſtles <hi>ad Smyrn. &amp; ad Polyc.</hi> out of his care
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:115813:90"/> and affection to his Church at Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochia, having received news of their good eſtate, and finding himſelf in the like, he deſires the Church of Smyrna and Polycarpus to chuſe one to go with their letters to Antiochia, whom he will have called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (ſo it ſhould be read not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a meſſenger in matters belonging to God, to certifie them of his good eſtate, and to congratulate with them of their own: this office it ſeemeth, requireth no impoſition of hands, and therefore that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by which Ignatius deſireth them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point it, ſignifieth, as it ſhould ſeem, not Ordination but Election, by the ſame reaſon, as that of the Apoſtle. The reſt that is brought to avouch this new conceit, is the words of Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naras, upon the firſt of the Canons of the Apoſtles, where in down right terms he delivereth the uſe of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to come from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:115813:91"/> of giving voices by holding up hands, uſed in the Church at firſt, to diſcern on w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſide moſt voices were, from whence it came afterwards to be uſed for impoſition of hands. But let them bethink themſelves, that if theſe Presbyters were made by Saul and Barnabas by holding up hands of the people, then were they not made by impoſition of their own hands, for if we take that ſenſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the other muſt needs be excluded. And then let me ask, if it be a thing reaſonable, to meaſure the ſenſe of the Apoſtles language, by what was done at Athens, rathen then by that, which among the Jews, from whence the faith of Chriſt was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, was known and in uſe. Or to imagine, that the Apoſtle, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the faſhion of Greekiſh commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, never heard of in after ages of the Church, ſhould balk the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, which the people of God had
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:115813:91"/> received from Moſes, which was from old time frequented in creating their Sanedrin Judges, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in their own perſons practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, which the Church hath alwayes obſerved in promoting of Miniſters, ſignifying the overſhadowing of the Holy Ghoſt, and praying to obtein it. To the words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle and Ignatius, ſeeing they have in them no appearance of reſolute ſenſe, let me anſwer two wayes. Firſt, though they were not ordained by impoſition of hands, yet it is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, they ſhould be called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, uſing the word in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſenſe, for thoſe that are ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or conſtituted, in any form, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this form was ſo frequented in divers occaſions. As, for the purpoſe, among the Jews, all their Rabbies are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſignifieth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ordained by impoſition of hands, becauſe at
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:115813:92"/> the firſt ſo they were made, though they be not promoted after that form, but made, as ſince they are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily made, by writing or word of mouth, as Rab. Moſes, in Sanedrin, chap. 4. writeth. But in the ſecond place obſerve the words which Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius writing to Polycarpus about this matter, uſeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where for the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting of a perſon fit for this purpoſe, he adviſeth him to convent one of theſe Aſſemblies wherein they uſed to adviſe about Ordinations, as hath been ſaid. And therefore it ſeemeth no inconvenience to think that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth him to be ordained to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Whereupon it will not be amiſſe to inquire a little further to what Miniſtery in the Church ſuch a perſon may be thought to be ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wherein if we fail not, perhaps it
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:115813:92"/> will make us able to give a fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture at that of the Apoſtle by the correſpondence of the caſes. Ignatius in the Epiſtle to the Philadelphians, writeth to them, for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as here he doth to thoſe of Smyrna, though the ſenſe is hitherto diſguiſed in the printed copies, in which the words runne thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which words it is plain make no ſenſe. But I have ſeen the written copy of an old tranſlation of theſe Epiſtles in barbarous Latine, in Caius Colledge Library here with us, in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> theſe words are rendred thus, <hi>Quod annunciatum eſt mihi pacem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere Eccleſiam quae eſt in Antiochia Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae: Decens eſt vos ut Eccleſiam Dei Ordinare Diaconum ad intercedendum</hi>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:115813:93"/> 
               <hi>illic Dei interceſsionem in congaudere ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis in idipſum factis &amp; glorific are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> He that made this tranſlation read here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſtead of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> now is read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and maketh it no ſenſe, and this is without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the true reading, for it followeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And where he ſaith afterwards, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is agreeable to the charitableneſſe of thoſe times to think, that neighbour Churches ſent ſome their Biſhops, ſome their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyters or Deacons to comfort, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, to congratulate with his Church of Antiochia in their Biſhops abſence; and reaſonable it is that he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thoſe of Smyrna and Philadelphia ſhould ordain a Deacon for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but that they ſhould make a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop for it, as now we reade it, is without the compaſſe of common
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:115813:93"/> ſenſe to imagine. Be it then reſolved, that it is no other then a Deacon which Ignatius deſires theſe of Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na as well as thoſe of Philadelphia to Ordain, to carry this meſſage. And let me have leave to conjecture, that thoſe whom the Apoſtle in the place alledged 2. Cor. viii. 23. calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>meſſengers of the Churches,</hi> were by their rank in the Church no other then Deacons: Which is by like reaſon to be ſaid of Epaphroditus whom S. Paul. Phil. ii. 25. calleth <hi>the Apoſtle of the Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians, and Miniſter of his neceſsities,</hi> and perhaps of Andronicus &amp; Junias, reading it for the name of a man and not of a woman, Rom. xvi. 7. where they are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>noted among the Apoſtles.</hi> For the name Apoſtle is relative to him by whom he is ſent; the Apoſtles of Chriſt, are Chriſts meſſengers, the Apoſtles of Churches, are the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:115813:94"/> which they ſend on common buſineſſe. Now ye ſhall often find in the practice of the ancient Church, that Deacons were ſent to forrein Churches about the buſineſſe of their own. And this practice beareth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the Synagogue, for thoſe that are called among them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of whom Epiphanius ſpeaketh in theſe terms deſcribing their office, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that they are by interpretation Deacons or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> are by another name called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is <hi>verbatim</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the Synagogue,</hi> becauſe it is like theywere wont to be imployed about buſineſſe of the Synagogue. And therefore if the perſon of whom S. Paul ſpeaketh be no other then S. Luke the Evangeliſt as many think, and the ſubſcription of that Epiſtle beareth, when he ſets him forth thus,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:115813:94"/> 2. Cor. viii. 8, 18, 19. <hi>Now we have ſent with him our brother whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel</hi> (or in preaching the Goſpel) <hi>through all the Churches, and not that alone, but was ordained by the Churches to travel with us, with this grace which is miniſtred by us,</hi> I ſhall not ſtick to think of him as of Philip the Deacon and Evangeliſt, that for his rank he was ordained a Deacon by conſent of many Churches, in ſome of them, to diſpenſe the almes they ſent with S. Paul to Hieruſalem, though for his perſonall grace he was an Evangeliſt. Nay if the queſtion be asked, to what rank Timothy was ordained by that impoſition of hands of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, mentioned by the Apoſtle, my anſwer muſt be, ſeeing Presbyters are for the overſight of their Churches, and Biſhop he was none till he undertook his charge at Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that he was ordained Deacon by that Church to give attendance on S.
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:115813:95"/> Paul in his travels, for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his perſonall grace of Evangeliſt was very opportune, for thus much Ignatius hath ſaid writing to the Deacons at Trallis, <hi>That the Deacons were ſuch as miniſtred a pure and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miniſtery, as holy Stephen to bleſſed James, and Timothy and Linus to Paul, and Anacletus &amp; Clemens to Peter.</hi> Now as for Zonaras, that had a mind to ſhew his reading in Demoſthenes, or the like Greek Authours, and improve it by expounding the Canons accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, it is but ſending him to Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamon for his anſwer, who writing upon the ſame Canon, hath met with this impertinence of his, with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoydable reaſon to convince his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, which is, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Canons, cannot mean Election by moſt voyces, becauſe the choyce of a Biſhop is done by all the Biſhops of the Province, according to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of Nice and Antiochia alledged
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:115813:95"/> afore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas the Ordination, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is performed by two or three, by the tenour of that Canon of the Apoſtles. And therefore Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellus, by the way, did not right to alledge Balſamon, for one that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds Zonaras in this conceit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is plain he hath laid him upon his back. To which let me adde this. The v. Canon of Laodicea provideth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>Elections,</hi> ſaith Zona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras: for this Canon he alledgeth for his purpoſe, becauſe at Elections, ſcandals were ript up, and mens faults examined. And ſo ſay all thoſe, that allow the people intereſſe, of appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or excepting againſt thoſe that ſtood to be ordained, but he that looketh as farre as the xiii. Canon of that Councel, will never allow the people right of Electing by moſt voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces according to that Councel which provideth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:115813:96"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That the choice of ſuch as are to be placed in the rank of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, muſt not be yielded to the people.</hi> Now it is well enough known, that many times at theſe aſſemblies for making of Miniſters the votes of the people, deſiring ſuch or ſuch perſons for Biſhops, or Presbyters, or others, prevented the order in practice, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating ſuch before hand, as they deſired to have made, as it is to be ſeen, in the eminent examples of S. Auguſtine among Presbyters, and S. Ambroſe among Biſhops. Neither was it an inconvenience, that thoſe which ordained ſhould balk the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed courſe, to give ſatisfaction to the peoples deſire when there was appeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that it was bred upon a due opinion of merit in the perſon recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. And the caſe is in a manner the ſame, when the beſt Chriſtian Emperours, did oftentimes of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:115813:96"/> nominate to the Biſhopricks of the chief ſeats of the Empire, where the State was moſt intereſſed in the condition of the perſon to be ordained. For in this they proceeded, as thoſe, in whom reſted all the right of the people in that Common-wealth. The Biſhops proceeding to do their office, upon due knowledge and approbation of the perſon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examining the courſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, as not ſo near concerning their charge. And thus it is plain, that the Apoſtles did not leave the choice of Matthias, or the ſeven Deacons, at large to the people: but qualifying the perſons by their dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, in whom thoſe qualities were found, (reſting indifferent themſelves) they referred to the knowledge of the people. For ſo we reade of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias, Acts i. 21. <hi>Of theſe men that have companied with us, ever ſince the Lord Jeſus went in and out among</hi>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:115813:97"/> 
               <hi>us, muſt one be choſen, to be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his reſurrection with us.</hi> And of the ſeven Deacons, Acts vi. 3. <hi>Wherefore, Brethren, look you out among you ſeven men of honeſt report, full of the holy Ghoſt, and wiſdome, whom we may appoint over this buſineſſe:</hi> but had the perſons been found not qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, no man will be ſo groſſe as to think the Apoſtles might not, or ought not, to controll the choice. And though it were granted, which with truth cannot be granted, that the Presbyters aforeſaid were made by Saul and Barnabas, upon moſt voyces of the people, yet if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to them, the Nomination of the perſons, the intereſſe of the people will be leſſe, rather then more, then the people of this Church uſeth at the preſent though not in themſelves, yet in the Patrones of Churches, to whom the Church yieldeth it, in the name of the people, in reſpect to the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:115813:97"/> merit of thoſe, that built or indowed Churches: at leaſt if the ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non were in uſe. For though it be a little without the terms of my ſubject, yet let me ſay this word, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Paſtours in rurall Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, that by the order thus farre ſpecified, it muſt needs come from the Mother-church, out of the gremialls of it. In the firſt ages of the Church, there is little or no mention but of Presbyteries in groſſe, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſervice of Mother-churches, whereof hitherto we ſpeak. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when the faith was planted, and Congregations ordered, in the Territories of thoſe Cities, or Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſes of thoſe Churches, we find in the 25. Canon of Neoceſarea a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence made between the Presbyters of them, whereof ſome are called there <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, others, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe of the Mother-church, thoſe of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Congregations. And by the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:115813:98"/> Canon of Chalcedon mentioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, forbidding all Ordinations at large, but for the ſervice of the city Church, or other depending on it, it appeareth, that by virtue of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination in the Mother Church, wherein the people concurred no otherwiſe then hath been ſaid, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Presbyters or other Miniſters were inveſted in their charge of thoſe Churches. Before that time it is to be obſerved that the Councel of Nice, Can. xv. forbidding Miniſters to paſſe from Citie to Citie, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops, Presbyters or Deacons) that is, to leave their own Mother-church, to ſerve in another Mother-church, proceedeth in theſe terms, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>It ſeemed good to put down the faſhion that is come up in ſome parts beſides the Rule.</hi> Signifying that the Rule of the Church from the beginning
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:115813:98"/> was to ordain Miniſters in Mother-churches, for the ſervice of thoſe Mother-churches. But in the xvi. Canon next following, it is further provided, that they ſhall be conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to return to their firſt charges, in theſe terms, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>They muſt be conſtrained by all means to return into their own Dioceſes.</hi> For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons ſignifieth the countrey lying to the Citie of the Mother-church, which we call the Dioceſe. This Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſpeaking of Presbyters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and not of Biſhops, beſides the voyding of ſuch attempts, which is done in the xv. Canon afore, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding a courſe to conſtrain them to return, extendeth further then the other did, to Presbyters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons in countrey Cures, whereas that reſted in the Mother-church. So the 3. Canon of Antiochia, ſo
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:115813:99"/> the xv. of the Apoſtles, providing that Miniſters ſhould not leave <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>their Dioceſes,</hi> as was ſaid, ſpeak plain to let us know how much the Cures of the whole Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, and the Perſons by whom they were exerciſed, were in the diſpoſing of the Mother Church, when it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that the Miniſters of them could not depart, to ſerve in or under other Churches, till they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed their firſt charge, with letters of licence from the Mother-church, which they called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſorias.</hi> Wherein, the condition of the Church, is juſt that of the Greekiſh Colonies. They were wont to have their Prieſts ſent them from the Mother-cities, and reſerved the firſt fruits which were the Prieſts due, for an honour to their founders: as Thucydides lib. 1. and his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſt writeth, alledging this for an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of that warre, becauſe thoſe
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:115813:99"/> of Corcyra, neglected their Mother-citie of Corinth, in that accuſtomed right. So all rurall Congregations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at firſt nothing but colonies of the Faith, planted from Mother-churches, founded in Mother-cities, from the time of the Apoſtles, it was but reaſon they ſhould receive their Paſtors from the head of the Dioceſe, where the charge of overſeeing, as well as plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them belonged. The right of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting then, yielded by the Church (to the people or to the Patrone, it concerns not in her regard) if it were to Orders as well as to Cures, were more then the People ſhould have, in chuſing out of thoſe which Saul and Barnabas might nominate. But he that would have the people, both name the perſons, and chuſe out of thoſe themſelves named, neglecting impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, or injoyning it upon the choice, muſt firſt put the Epiſtles to Timothy &amp; Titus out of the Bible,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:115813:100"/> leaſt at the firſt inſight, that appeare to belong to the office of men of their place, the account whereof lyeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their charge. As for the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting of Biſhops, fit it is in the firſt place, proviſion be made, for the intereſſe of the State, as well in orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the choyces, as in approving the perſons choſen, that no man be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, prejudiciall to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. But yet that courſe, in which the Chriſtian Emperours of ancient times, interpoſed themſelves to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the perſons being acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be beſides the Rule, did not deſtroy it in all but balk it for the time. Now if the people from the beginning had a due ſhare of intereſſe in giving conſent to thoſe which were to be ordained their Presbyters, much more muſt we needs think that it was due and of right, that the votes of the Presbyters, and conſent of the people, ſhould go before, in deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:115813:100"/> the Perſons, under whom and with whom they were to guide and be guided in Spirituall matters. As for impoſition of hands of neighbour Biſhops, with whom the unitie of the Church was to be preſerved by the Ordained, it was not then the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of a thing done, but the ſubſtance of the Act, reſting upon the account of them that did it by virtue of the Apoſtles charge. And therefore though it is not eaſie for me to judge, how farre it concerneth the Church to retain the Primitive form, yet it is eaſie for indifferent perſons to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, how much is required to the retaining of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="192" facs="tcp:115813:101"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The rule of cenſuring perſons ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, directed to Timothy alone. The office exerciſed according to the other parts of it.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>Something would here be ſaid in the laſt place of that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth upon theſe two laſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, of Penance and Ordination: that is, the cenſure of offenſes, whether in doctrine or manners of perſons Ordained; becauſe the Apoſtle ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to referre this to Timothy, that is, to the Biſhop alone, not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning any concurrence of his Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in it. For ſo we reade, 1. Tim. v. 19, 20. <hi>Againſt an Elder receive not an accuſation, but under two or three witneſſes. Them that ſinne rebuke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all, that others alſo may have fear.</hi> But having hitherto ſhewed, that our Lord in the Goſpel hath appointed
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:115813:101"/> matters of particular offenſe, to come before the Conſiſtory of Biſhop and Presbyters: That the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in divers matters belonging to the Government of the Church, uſed their aſſiſtance: That in the Primitive times of the Church, even under the Apoſtles, matters of Cenſure and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination both were wont to paſſe by the Presbyters, but in the Aſſemblies of Chriſtian people: Let me referre this to al indifferent perſons to judge, whether the ſame courſe of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were in likelyhood obſerved in the cenſure of Presbyters. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles direction, regulating what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to admit, is directed to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie alone; for the meaning is not, that two or three ſhould be preſent when it is put in, but that it ſhould not be admitted, but, (as the Syriack tranſlateth it) <hi>upon the mouth,</hi> that is, the word, of two or three witneſſes: But the cenſure of reproof is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:115813:102"/> to paſſe in the congregation, when he ſaith, <hi>them that ſinne,</hi> that is, them that are found in fault, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke before all,</hi> that others may have fear, no otherwiſe then the cenſure of the Apoſtle did and was preſcribed to do, 1. Cor. v. 4. 2. Cor. ii. 6. and therefore we are to think, that the examination of ſuch cauſes muſt paſſe, as others of like nature, by him with the Presbyters, to whom the Apoſtle had aſſigned a charge of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the Church there, Acts xx. 28, 35. So the keyes of the Church given to S. Peter and to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, were nevertheleſſe intended to be exerciſed by the Church, as hath been ſaid. So the charge of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating Hereticks is directed to Titus alone, Titus iii. 10. But we have no reaſon therefore to imagine, that Titus is directed to proceed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in it, then we know the Church was wont to proceed in
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:115813:102"/> Cenſures of that nature, according to that which hath been ſaid. And ſo it is in the caſe that followeth a little after, verſe 22. <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other mens ſinnes;</hi> where the rule of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations is directed to Timothy alone, yet have we no cauſe to believe that it was practiced by him, otherwiſe then according to the form aforeſaid, joyning with him the Ptesbyters in impoſition of hands, as was practiced by the Apoſtle. The eminence of their place is to be acknowledged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtles inſtructions, for managing theſe matters, are directed to them alone: But their courſe of proceeding muſt be meaſured by that which we know otherwiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb n="196" facs="tcp:115813:103"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Retaining the primitive form, Biſhops cannot be aboliſhed. How Aerius is counted an Heretick. All diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt Biſhops occaſioned by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Presbyteries. To what purpoſe they might be reſtored.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THat which hath been ſaid, being intended to repreſent the form delivered in Scripture by the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hiſtoricall truth and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive practice, concerneth no more as every man ſees, then the government of Mother-churches contained in Mother-cities: Becauſe that is all the Scripture hath expreſſed. But what influence and effect this ought to have in the preſent ſtate of the Church, now that Dioceſes are divided, Churches built, and congregations aſſigned, is not for a private perſon to particularize, unleſſe he meant to
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:115813:103"/> build Churches (as ſome men do Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles) in the air. Let it be enough to ſay thus much in generall, which every man muſt think that believeth what hath been ſaid to be true, that he that aimeth at the Primitive form, and that which cometh neareſt the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our Lord and his Apoſtles, muſt not think of deſtroying Biſhops but of reſtoring their Presbyteries. Were it but an humane Ordinance of yeſterday, eſtabliſhed by due courſe of right, let me be bold to ſay, that if Aerius withdraw his ſubmiſſion to it, he muſt come within Epiphanius his liſt of Hereticks: not underſtanding an Heretick in S. Auguſtines ſenſe, (wherein Tertullian in his book <hi>de praeſcript.</hi> went afore him) to be none but he that will not believe ſome point of doctrine neceſſary, as the means of ſalvation, to be believed: but according to the latitude of the word, taking all to be Hereticks that
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:115813:104"/> make Sects, and aſſemble themſelves apart beſides the Church of God law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſettled. This ſenſe is uſed in Can. 6. <hi>Conc.</hi> 1. <hi>Conſtantinop.</hi> where they are counted Hereticks that hold the ſound faith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And this latitude it ſeemeth Epiphanius compriſed, becauſe he reckoneth the Quartadecimani in the roll of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. Theſe, when the poſition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſeparation is grounded, is not of weight (ſetting their ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſide) to ſeparate them from the inviſible Church, are ſince according to the Authors named afore by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per term called Schiſmaticks, though Hereticks in the proper ſenſe ſeparate no leſſe then they do. And of this crime my earneſt deſire is, that thoſe which have ſeparated themſelves from this Church of England upon this quarrel of government by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, or the like unjuſt or unſufficient
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:115813:104"/> cauſes, may ſtand acquitted, though how they will acquit themſelves of it, I cannot yet perceive. But if the rank of Biſhops over their Presbyters be not onely a juſt humane Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but eſtated in poſſeſſion of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years without deceit or violence at the beginning, let me have leave to think it will be hard to ſhew a better title of humane right for any eſtate upon the earth. How much more when the poſſeſſion is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouched to have been delivered from the hands and time of the Apoſtles, muſt it needs ſeem ſtrange that the ſucceſſours of their place ſhould be deſtroyed by the ſons of their faith? Be it pardonable for our neighbours and Brethren of the reformed Churches abroad to have overſeen the ſucceſſion of the Apoſtles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could not diſcern it, as they found it blended with ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of acceſſories, eſpecially in
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:115813:105"/> the perſons of men that hated to be reformed: But among us, there hath been time to plead the right to the quick, and though not without eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of debate, which intereſſe breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, yet alwayes with advantage to the true tenure: And among the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſpeech that this time hath bred, we have heard little or nothing as yet of new reaſons to quell the cauſe with. So that before advancing new plea, the old right deſcending from ſuch hands, ſtandeth now in as good terms as ever heretofore. As for the point of peace within our ſelves, and correſpondence with our neighbours, be it conſidered how large S. Hierom (of all Church writers leaſt favourable to the Order, as he that found himſelf pinched with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Jeruſalem) hath been never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe in acknowledging, that the peace of particular Churches could not be preſerved without it. To which
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:115813:105"/> we muſt adde the remembrance of ſo many happy dayes as this Church ſince the Reformation hath ſeen, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch ruptures as have fallen out in other parts, by the benefit of it, among a people alwayes obſerved to be of all others moſt daring to innovate opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in matters of religion eſpecially, as well as in thoſe that concern other knowledge. But he that calleth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance that correſpondence which in ancient times was actuated between Churches of ſeverall nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; people, <hi>commercio formatarum,</hi> as Optatus ſpeaketh, by traffique of thoſe letters of correſpondence, which under ſet forms were wont to paſſe between Biſhops, in the name of their Churches, (the true form of that unitie which our Lord commended to his Church, after it was become Catholick) muſt needs lament to ſee that moſt beautifull peace of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in ancient time, defaced and
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:115813:106"/> loſt, by the fault of them that hate to be reformed, in the diſſenſions of Chriſtendome, alledged to deſtroy it. The honour and eſteem which the learned of the reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad have profeſſed of the ſtate of our Churches, and our charity in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing the neceſſities of theirs, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the efficacy of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery which they uſe, will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient through Gods goodneſſe to actuate the correſpondence we deſire to preſerve with them, without thoſe innovations which they never requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at our hands to ſuch purpoſe. But he that acknowledgeth and is glad to ſee theſe heads ſtand in their right place, looking back upon their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which was to ſucceed the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles over ſeverall Presbyteries, in the place which they held over all for the time, muſt needs miſſe their relatives, the bodies of theſe Presbyteries, in the government of Churches. And
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:115813:106"/> though that alteration cannot be charged upon any man, which is come to paſſe through time and inſenſible cuſtome: eſpecially, ſeeing it cannot be counted an alteration in this Church of England, becauſe we are to think it had prevailed in the Church before this Nation received the Faith: yet muſt it needs be remembred, by him that believeth all the evil conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which this government is charged with, whether in opinion or truth, to have come from the diſcharge of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyteries from their part of the office. One particular no man need to be nice in reckoning to be of that nature, though it is not in the power of one man (were he as much in love as I am with the primitive form) or ſcarce of one age, without a publick act to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it: That is the committing of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction at large, (even that which is proper and eſſentiall to the Church, by the power of the keyes which our
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:115813:107"/> Lord hath given it, as hath been ſaid) in effect, to Lay perſons, Which juriſdiction though for the preſent, it paſſe not upon preſent adviſe, but upon Laws of the Church for the purpoſe, yet ſo long as Laws are generall and few, Caſes particular and numberleſſe, will alwayes deſerve to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, with mature and charitable adviſe of thoſe to whoſe charge our Lord firſt committed it, if we mean to attain the ends of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and example. Though the profeſſion by which it is miniſtred deſerve to retain the rank it hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in regard of thoſe other points of juriſdiction in charitable cauſes, by the favour of Princes, and laws of Common-wealths annexed to the Church, paſſing as it doth, by the laws whereof they profeſſe knowledge. This inconvenience, if ſuch it be counted, ſeemeth to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:115813:107"/> from that unſenſible change whereof hath been ſaid: for had the Presbyteries continued, as at the beginning, upon the exerciſe of this Diſcipline of Penance, it is not to be thought that power could have been ſo lightly aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as from one, wherein a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber had their intereſſe. But this, and the like conſequences ſeem to have brought this undue opinion upon the Church Government, that as Cathedrall Churches long ſince, ſo now the State of Biſhops among indifferent men is counted a matter of indifference, which had they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the Primitive charge, muſt needs have been counted, as count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they ought to be, inviolable. And therefore though as the caſe ſtandeth, it is neither poſſible nor deſired, to call the whole Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of a Dioceſe to a ſhare in the publick government, yet let me
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:115813:108"/> have leave to ſay, that the next courſe to retrive the Primitive form, with the wholeſome grounds and conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it, is to reeſtate theſe Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries in Cathedrall Churches, and perhaps, in other populous places, ſeats of juriſdictions, where the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe is great, furniſhing them with number of men of abilities, and joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with and under the Biſhops, for aſſiſtance in all parts of the office hitherto proved common to both. It ſeems the means that hath brought to paſſe that inſenſible change where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we ſpeak, was from the beginning no other then this, becauſe the form of proceeding in particular Churches was never regulated by Canons of the Church, but left to particular cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome: And therefore it is paſt my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion how more right ſhould be done, then diſtributing the common charge into particular intereſſe, by ſuch rules as may beſt expreſſe thoſe
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:115813:108"/> generall terms, which the pureſt Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times were content with; that as without the Biſhop nothing to be done, ſo the Biſhop to do nothing without advice of his Presbyters. The performance of divine ſervice in the Cathedrall, common ſenſe finds too ſlight a work for ſuch perſons; the cures of all Churches within ſuch populous places, if they belonged to their titles, would be a work ſutable to ſuch prime abilities. Then the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the power of the keyes in the diſcipline of Penance, Triall and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of perſons preſented to Cures, or aſſiſtance of Cures, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to laws, (excluding all Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons without ſuch title) Cenſure of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes in doctrine, or life of perſons ordained, alwayes under the Biſhop, and for his aſſiſtance, are works that require mature adviſe, and paſſe beſt in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon for ſatisfaction to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, matters of religion being by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:115813:109"/> more popular then the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. If this be not enough, ſuch may be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s abilities that all theſe Presbyteries may become ſchools of the Prophets, and Seminaries of able Preachers through the ſeverall Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions or Dioceſes: A thing wiſhed on all hands, but not to be expected without means to bring it to paſſe. This hath been alwayes deſired at the hands of Cathedrall Churches, and ſome ſteps of it remain ſtill in ſome of ours, &amp; though the ſtaple of this edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation being long ſince drained from other places to the two Univerſities, the charge hath been ſuſtained by them alone with unſpeakable benefit, to the Church, as well as to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, yet the aſſiſtance of theſe places with them, for the ſervice of the Church, is not to be counted their prejudice, leaving intire unto them the place they poſſeſſe, of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
